<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An appeal to Caesar wherein gold and silver is proved to the Kings Majestie's royal commodity : which, by the lawes of the kingdom, no person of what degree soever but the Kings Majestie and his Privy Council can give licence to transport either gold or silver ... / by Tho. Violet ...</title>
            <author>Violet, Thomas, fl. 1634-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34727</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14576253</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14576253</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1077:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An appeal to Caesar wherein gold and silver is proved to the Kings Majestie's royal commodity : which, by the lawes of the kingdom, no person of what degree soever but the Kings Majestie and his Privy Council can give licence to transport either gold or silver ... / by Tho. Violet ...</title>
                  <author>Violet, Thomas, fl. 1634-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 57, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coinage --  England.</term>
               <term>Precious metals --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APPEAL TO CAESAR: WHEREIN GOLD And SILVER Is Proved to be the Kings Majeſties <hi>ROYAL COMMODITY.</hi> WHICH By the Lawes of the Kingdom, no Perſon of what Degree ſoever, but the KINGS MAJESTIE, and his Privy Councel, can give Licence to Tranſport either Gold or Silver to any Perſon, after it is Landed in any part of the Kingdome of <hi>England.</hi> That this Great and Sacred Truſt cannot be changed into the Hands of any Perſon, Perſons, or Corporations whatſoever, without changing or diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sacred Power of his Majeſtie, it being againſt his Crown and Dignity. Humbly Preſented to his Moſt Sacred MAJESTIE, and his Moſt Honourable Privy Councel, in oppoſition to ſome Merchants, who are Endeavouring, upon feigned Pretences, to diſpoſſeſſe his Majeſtie of this Royal Truſt, and to have it Confirmed by Act of Parliament, to Tranſport at the Merchants pleaſure, Forreign Bullion and Coine freely, after it is Imported into the Kingdom, and make it a Free Merchandize for their private profit, to the Damage of the whole Kingdom in general.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. VIOLET</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Goldſmith.</p>
            <bibl>MATTH. 22. 21.</bibl>
            <q>Render therefore unto Ceſar the things which are Ceſars, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102645:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS moſt Excellent Majeſtie: And to the LORDS of his MAIESTIES moſt Honourable <hi>PRIVY CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCEL.</hi> The Humble Petition of <hi>THO. VIOLET</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Goldſmith.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread Soveraign!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Your Majeſties moſt Humble, Loyal, and Dutiful Subject, humbly upon my Knees preſent this inſuing Narrative to Your Sacred Majeſty, and to Your moſt honourable and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Councell. I had not preſumed to have medled, with this cauſe and Argument, but that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſee with what eagerneſſe ſome Merchants of <hi>London</hi> thought to ſteal one of the prime Flowers of your Majeſties Crown, (from your Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and Your moſt honourable Privy Councell) before the Riſing of this bleſſed Parliament. True it is, Gold and Silver all over the World is a currant Merchandize, it anſwereth all things, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things under the Sun.</p>
            <p>But ſo, that in all Kingdoms, Gold and Silver is a Kingly Merchandize, and only at the Kings Diſpoſe and Will, and not at the diſpoſe of the Merchants, to be tranſported at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. May it pleaſe Your Majeſty, by Twenty Acts of Parliament, the Lawes of this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in all Ages, hath inveſted it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102645:3"/> in the moſt Sacred Hands of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and their Privy Councel, and none other (whomſoever, either Lords, Biſhops, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons).</p>
            <p>The Reaſons upon peruſall of this Narrative, Your Majeſty will find to have been done, upon moſt wiſe, juſt, and great conſideration, both for the Honour, Strength, and Defence of the Kings Sacred Perſon, His Crown, and Dignity, and Safetie of the people.</p>
            <p>The Money, Bullion, Gold and Silver of this Kingdom in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, (till theſe perillous head-ſtrong Fanatick daies) hath been counted the chief Strength of the Kingdom, the very Soul of the Militia, and the Sinews of Warre and Peace) in Your Majeſties moſt Sacred Hands, and in Your Privy Councels, the Law of this Kingdom hath inveſted it, (and in none other of Your Majeſties Subjects of what condition ſoever,) and there let it ſafely remain to the end of this World.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſties moſt humble Subject, upon his bended Knees, prayes Your Majeſty to keep this Sacred Trust intire in Your Hand, and not to diminiſh the leaſt tittle, or branch of it.</p>
            <p>O never ſuffer it to be at the will of the Merchant (leaſt Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, which God defend, giving ſome fawning ſpaniels this Authority, as they deſire, out of Your Sacred Hands) You give an oppertunity in a few years, that the breed of them may turn Maſtives, and ſo they may have a power to fly in the Face of Your Sacred Majeſty, as ſome of them did to Your Majeſties Royall Father of bleſsed memory, which God defend; <hi>Fore-warn'd, Fore-arm'd:</hi> I humbly think I deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to live, ſhould I not ſay this.</p>
            <p>The Gold and Silver of the Nation, either Forreign Coyne, or Ingot, or the currant Coin of the Kingdom, is the ſoul of the Militia, and ſo all wiſe men know it, that thoſe that command the Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the Kingdom, either Coin, or Bullion, to have it free at their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102645:3"/> to be Judges of the conveniency and inconveniency, or to hinder, or give leave to tranſport Gold and Silver at their pleaſure, is the great Wheell of the State, a moſt Royall Prerogative inherent in Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, Your Heirs and Succeſſors, (and none other whomſoever, but by Your Majeſties Licence, and cannot be parted with to any Perſons, but by Your Majeſties moſt eſpeciall Grant;) your Majeſty, and your Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Councell being by the Law the only proper Judges, to have liberty to ſend to your Friends the Gold and Silver of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Upon ſuch juſt Reaſons of State, as your Majeſty, and Privy Councell ſhall judg fit for the due relief of your Friends, and Allies, to offend your Enemy, and defend your Imperiall Crown, and Dignity, and ſtrengthen your Friends.</p>
            <p>As Queen <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> ſeverall times aſſiſted <hi>HENRY</hi> the Great King of <hi>France,</hi> your Majeſties Royall Grandfather; and the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> with vaſt ſums of Gold and Silver.</p>
            <p>The like Royall prerogative is in the Crown, upon Petition of the Merchants, ſetting forth their juſt Reaſons, and at your pleaſure your Majeſty to give them leave to ſend Forreign Gold and Silver either to the <hi>Indies,</hi> or any part of Chriſtendom; but ſo as your Majeſty, as all your Royall Predeceſsors, and your Privy Councell being in Commiſſion by your Majesty for that ſervice, are the only proper Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of this buſineſſe, and have the Lock and Key to diſpence with the penall Statutes, to give leave to ſend ſo much Gold and Silver of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Bullion, or the Coin of the Kingdom, as your Majeſty ſhall pleaſe in your wiſdom for to grant, and to what Prince, or Country, but not at the will of any other Perſon whomſoever.</p>
            <p>Your Petitioner humbly prayes upon my Knees, for your Majeſties honor, for your Majesties ſafety, for the ſafety and greatneſse of all your Lords and Gentry, for the ſafety of all your People, that your Majesty keep this Royall Truſt intire, and the ſame always in your Majeſty, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102645:4"/> your moſt honourable Privy Councels hands, as the Appell of your Eye. Gold and Silver is a Merchandize all over the World, true, but in King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms it is a Kingly Merchandize, and not to be tranſported without the Kings leave. What I hear ſay, I upon my Knees ſubmit to your Sacred Majeſties conſideration,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. 28. 1660</date>.</dateline> (and ſhall pray, &amp;c.)</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102645:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lord High Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord Steward of his MAIESTIES Houſh old, the Lord High Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord <hi>Roberts,</hi> all of his MAIESTIES moſt Honourable Privie Councell, Theſe humbly preſent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhips,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Humbly preſume for to Acquaint your Lordſhips, that I underſtand ſome Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to obtain an Act of Parliament, to make Gold and Silver a Merchandize, to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port freely at their will and pleaſure, as it is at this day at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and ſeveral other Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths in <hi>Christendome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">If this do not ſatisfie your Lordſhips, I have it at large to ſhew this miſchief, but I hope I ſhall not need to ſay more to this buſineſſe to ſtopit.</note>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> I am none of the Councel or Committee for Trade, and ſo it may be preſumption in me to intermeddle, to ſay any thing in this buſineſſe; but my Lords, a Stander by may ſee more in the Game then the Gameſters: I am no Lawyer, yet I humblie ſay, I know this point concerning the giving libertie to Merchants to tranſport money, and what the damage may be to his Majeſtie, to his Lords of the Councel, and to the Kingdom in general, as well as many others that are in Commiſſion for the Regulating of Trade.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> I have bin writing on this Argument above this moneth, and ſhall be ready to preſent to his Majeſtie, and his Privie Councel (within this week) a Paper that ſhall unfold the many miſchiefs and dangers the Merchants would expoſe the King and the Kingdom into, had they this Power in their hands: the Merchants ſhould they obtain this their deſire, and remove this Truſt out of his Majeſtie and his Privy Councels Hands, to be the only Iudges, to give leave to Merchants to tranſport Gold and Silver, would rob the King of one of his greateſt Prerogatives, and Flowers of the Crown, which by twenty Acts of Parliament and Proclamations, is only inveſted in the Kings Majeſtie, and his Privy Conncel; the granting the Merchants this Power, will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102645:5"/> bring an hundred inconveniences and miſchiefs to the King, Nobility, and Gentry, as I have at large to ſhew your Lordſhips and the Privy Councel, and if I do not ſatisfie his Majeſtie, your Lordſhips, and all his Privie Councel, of this that I ſay to be true, never let me have your Lordſhips good opinion, that I am either an honeſt man, or one that loves the Kings Safetie, Honour, and Greatneſſe, and the Honour of his Privy Councel.</p>
            <p>And therefore my moſt Humble Suit is to your Lordſhip, (my Lord Chancellour) that if this buſineſſe be called on at the Councel of Trade, and your Lordſhip be preſent there this day, as I hear you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be purpoſely about this buſineſſe, that your Lordſhip would be pleaſed, either to put off this buſineſſe for to have it argued before the Kings Majeſtie, or his Privie Councel at <hi>Whitehall</hi> ſometime next week, in the mean time I ſhall be ready to ſhew to your Lordſhip and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Councel, that it concerns his Majeſtie next to the <hi>Militia,</hi> to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and keep this great Truſt in his Majeſties Sacred hands, and in the Power of his Privie Councel, and no other perſon by the Law, can or ought to have the Priviledge, to give leave to tranſport Gold and Silver at their pleaſure, this being the ſoul of the <hi>Militia,</hi> they that have the money and the Peoples purſes, have virtually the Command in all Common-wealths of the Government; let who will have the Title, the Bankers have the power; and this priviledge is no where granted, but in Commonwealths, God defend <hi>England</hi> from the very name of a Commonwealth, for the Tragedies which were lately acted by ſome Merchants in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When we had no King in this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they have robbed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of all the Gold, and ſo now would work iniquity by a Law; but by Gods Aſſiſtance, I will diffect them, and lay the danger open to his Majeſtie, your Lordſhip, and the Kings moſt Honourable Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and ſtand or fall by your righteous Judgement, humbly praying for his Majeſties Safety, Honour and Service, that no further proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this great buſineſſe be argued, but before his Majeſtie, and his moſt prudent Privie Councel, within leſſe then a week I ſhall be ready with my Reaſons for what I ſay, to ſhew your Lordſhip, that ſo all the Lovers of the King might be ſatisfied of the Damage and Danger of removing this great Truſt, out of his Majeſties and his Privy Councels Hands. So I humbly reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. 27. 1660</date>.</dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Humble Servant THO. VIOLET.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102645:5"/>
            <head>For the Right Honourable the LORD CHANCELLOUR.</head>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip to give Order, That no further proceedings in this buſineſs be, but before, His Majeſty and his Privy Council at <hi>White-hall;</hi> and if His Majeſty and Privy Council give judgement againſt what I ſay to be true, I will loſe my life, when they hear this buſineſs examiued.</p>
            <p>WHereas the Merchants of <hi>London</hi> are endeavouring to get an Act of Parliament, to have liberty to export Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver freely without the Kings Majeſties and his moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Privy Councils leave, I humbly propound, for His Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and the ſafety, and honour of his Majeſty, that theſe humble Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals might be conſidered of before any further proceedings on that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be made. That his Majeſty and his honourable Privy Council be pleaſed to keep intire in their own hands the Licencing of all Gold and Silver after it is imported into this Kingdom, to be exported or Coined, as they ſhall ſee juſt cauſe, for the ſafety of the Nation, and ſafety and honour of his Majeſty and the Lords of his Council, and the ſafety and benefit of all his Majeſties Subjects of what condition ſoever; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſetled in the Crown ſo many hundred years by Acts of Parliament, as I ſhall prove it, this great and Sacred truſt be no way altered, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at this Juncture of time, this Kingdom being robbed of almoſt all its Gold and a great part of the Silver Coin, for the private profit of particular perſons, to the weakning of the Nation and the deſtruction of Trade<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this Royal truſt being one of the prime flowers of the Crown, and the very ſoul of the Militia, and it a right inherent onely in the King and his Privy Council, and there onely depoſited for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Years; whereby the King (only) by the Law can give leave and licence to tranſport Gold and Silver after it is imported into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that if you ever ſuffer this Roial truſt to be managed by the Merchant, and ſuffer all perſons by Act of Parliament to be free to tranſport Gold or Silver, either in Coin or Bullion, after it is imported and landed in England.</p>
            <p>You take away one of the principal Prerogatives and flowers of the Crown, deſtroying his Majeſties Mint in the Tower of London, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102645:6"/> lay a ſad foundation to give ſome factious Merchants of this Kingdom a ground to make new diſturbances, and leave the Nation weak and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of all Gold and Silver.</p>
            <p>The granting the Merchants this power they deſire, will bring a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand miſchiefs both on the King and Kingdom, which God defend. In all ages, till theſe Phanatick daies, the Gold and Silver after it was landed in the Kingdom, was held the Blood and Sinews of War and Peace, the Militia and ſtrength of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I ſhall humbly preſent unto you theſe following Reaſons for keeping this power intire in your Majeſty and Privy Council, and the King, Lords, and Commons cannot be ſafe to ſuffer any other perſon, upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever of the Crafty Merchant, to have the diſpoſals at their will, and for their private lucre to have the power by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to tranſport Gold or Silver either to the <hi>Indies,</hi> or other forraign Countries, or to any part of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>Without your Majeſties licence and order to take an exact account of what quantity of Gold or Silver is tranſported, to what Country, the Ship, with the Ships maſters name, either to the <hi>Indies,</hi> or any forraign Princes Country in Chriſtendom, or to any State, or Commonwealth; that ſo upon reaſons of State, they may either inlarg his Licences to the Merchant, or ſtraighten them according as the King and his Privy Council in their great wiſdom ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſty and Privy Council ever having regard that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome have alwayes ſuch plenty of Gold and Silver as may be for the honour of the King, and ſafety of the people, and to maintain Trade and Comerce in the Kingdom, to pay Rents, Cuſtoms, Exciſe, and Subſidies, to be a ſtrength and an honour to the Kingdom, and the King and his Privy Council to take the care to hinder Gold and Silver to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the Kings enemies.</p>
            <p>And of all and every part of theſe Heads and Branches, and real Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives; in all Ages the King, and none but the King, and his Privy Council, by Acts of Parliament, are the onely proper Iudges at their will, diſcretion and pleaſure, for the ſafety of the Kingdom, and no other perſon whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſeveral Reaſons of the Merchants to his Majeſty and his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Council, and upon their petition and requeſt the King can diſpence with the penalty of the Law, and give the Merchant licence to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port onely ſuch quantities of Gold or Silver, either forraign Coin or Ingots, or the currant Coin of the Kingdom, either in Gold or Silver, as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102645:6"/> the King and his privy Council ſhall think fit, for to carry on the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants trade in Chriſtendom, and out of Chriſtendom, to ſtrengthen his Majeſties friends, and offend his foes; and this is an undoubted right of his Majeſties Crown, and cannot be diſpenced with, or depoſited into the Merchants hands, or any other Subjects, either Lords ſpiritual or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, but to the diſhonour of his Majeſty and all the good people of the Kingdom, I do humbly prove it true for theſe Reaſons follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>If any perſon, of what degree ſoever, tranſport Gold or Silver without the Kings licence, the Laws and Statutes heretofore hath made it Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, both for Biſhops, Noblemen, or Commons, as I ſhall ſhew by the St atutes hereafter following, afterwards a praemunire, and at this day forfeiture and impriſonment during the Kings pleaſure, <hi>viz. 9 Edward 3. 2 Henry 4, cap. 4, 2 Henry 6, cap. 6. 18. Edw. 4, 1 Henry</hi> 8. 5 and 6 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>When the Kings Majeſty hath War with any Prince, by the Law the King may prohibit the Merchant to export Corn, Armes, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to them, or any other Commodities: the Law provides the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the exportations of Wool, Fullers earth, and Timber, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtructive to the Nation.</p>
            <p>Gold and Silver by the Law is free for any man to import, at what place he pleaſe to land it, without paying any Duty or Cuſtome, the reaſon whereof is, that the Merchant is obliged to Coin it, and upon the Coinage the King hath his duty paid, but once being landed, it cannot be tranſported but with leave from his Majeſty, or the forfeiture being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the party claiming the Gold and Silver ſo taken on ſhipboard, to be committed to priſon without Bail, till the King or his privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil pleaſe to diſcharge him: This is the Law, this the Cuſtome, before theſe mad Phanatick daies that we had no King in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this in all Ages was the practice both in your Exchequer and the Star chamber, for otherwiſe the Merchant, for his private profit would ſend all the Gold and Silver out of the Nation, and make the Kings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation wait upon the Merchants Exchange, as at this day it is with the Gold: The Merchants and ſome Goldſmiths have raiſed Gold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Kings proclamation: may it pleaſe your Majeſty, we want a Star chamber to puniſh them. I humbly leave it to conſideration, no Gold to be had under one ſhilling ſix pence in twenty ſhillings, more then ſilver; I humbly pray an Act might paſs this preſent Parliament againſt this abuſe of the Gold Coin, and ſeveral other abuſes and cheats
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102645:7"/> put on the Nobility and Gentry by the adulterating and undue making Gold and Silver Lace in <hi>London,</hi> whereby the wearers are daily cozened by courſe flight adulterate Gold and Silver, and by putting a ſlight body of Silver on a great threed of ſilk, to the damage of this Nation, above fifty thouſand pound a year, as I will prove it to your Majeſty and your Privy Council; and this is done for want of a Regulation of the Work-maſters and Workmen in <hi>London</hi> that make Gold and Silver Lace, without an Eſſay, or Fineneſſe, or proportion of Silver to Silk.</p>
            <p>I humbly deſire your Lordſhips to conſider what a loſs the King will have in his Cuſtomes, to ſuffer Gold and Silver to be exported at the pleaſure of the Merchant, and pay no Cuſtome; here will be, for the profit of particular Merchants, a Trade driven both inwards and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the King have neither Exciſe nor Cuſtome; for all the World knows, Gold and ſilver payes no duty inwards, it is free to be imported at the pleaſure of the Merchant, when and how, and where he pleaſe, for the reaſons aboveſaid:</p>
            <p>And if you give the Merchant leave to tranſport the Gold and Silver freely he imports, what is the King the better by this Trade of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, either inwards or outwards? let this be granted to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, to ſend out Silver and Gold freely, for their private profit, and in a few years they will leave neither Gold nor Silver in the Nation.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſty, It is profit that is ſome Merchants guide, not honour, nor the ſafety of the Nation, and this is moſt apparent by ſome mens actions and demands, touching this great buſineſſe; The King will loſe in point of His Exciſe, and Cuſtoms, for if the Merchant inveſt his Silver and Gold in Merchandies, the King hath thereby His Exciſe and Cuſtoms: the King will loſe in point of His Mintage; if no money be coyned, no profit by coynage: this hath made the Mint, a great part of their Work-houſes fall down: It is for the Kings honour to have His Kingdoms full of Gold and Silver, for His, and the Subjects de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>And if this Fanatick project ſhould take, the King loſes one of the principal prerogatives of His Crown, and Dignity; for thoſe that have the command of the peoples purſes, have the principal part of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Common-wealth trick, but tends to the undoing of a King, in all Countries where the Merchants can ſet up a banck, and tranſport money freely, as at <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> have not theſe men the command of the <hi>Militia,</hi> they are the peoples Princes, and virtually the Banckers have the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102645:7"/> power, riches, and ſtrength of the Common-wealth, let who will have the Title, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> &amp;c. but the Banker, and the hogan mogan Merchants have the power.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is clear, they have got the people by the money, and leave them nothing but ſome Stivers, and baſe money to buy victuals; and indeed the people have nothing but a paper credit; in a Kingdome the Merchants will never put up a banck, leaſt the King ſhould ſeize on it all, they will not allow a King to do that they practice.</p>
            <p>And I humbly ſay, it is not for the ſafety of the King, nor Lords, to let the Merchants have liberty to tranſport Silver or Gold at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to forreign Bancks, and Common-wealths, leaſt the Merchants in a year or two put the ſame trick on the King, and Kingdom, for all their current Silver, as at this day they have done for all the Gold of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let the greatneſſe of the Merchant be as a Hand-maid to the Kings greatneſſe, and ever ſubordinate to the King.</p>
            <p>Or elſe a confederation of twenty Merchants and Goldſmiths, ſhall make the Engliſh ſhilling, in ſpite of the Kings Proclamation, and againſt His Crown, and Dignity, and in deſpite of an Act of Parliament, to go for 13. d. every Engliſh ſhilling; twenty ſhillings, for twenty one ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings eight pence; let but the Merchants make Silver a Merchandize, as the Goldſmiths and Merchants have already done Gold.</p>
            <p>I beſeech your Majeſty to obſerv your Royal Father of bleſſed memory, never did by His Proclamation, or at his Mint in the <hi>Tower,</hi> raiſe the Gold coined at above twenty ſhillings a peece in payment. Doth not the Statute 5. and 6. of <hi>Edw.</hi> the ſixth, make it forfeiture of the value, for any perſon whomſoever, to utter, or put off Gold or Silver money at above the Kings Proclamation, and impriſonment during the Kings pleaſure? Do not above ten Proclamations ſay the ſame? this is the known Law. Yet at this day, by the confederation of ſome Merchants and Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths, in ſpite of this Law and Proclamations, for the Merchants and Goldſmiths private profit, the current Gold is not by any perſon to be had, a twenty ſhilling peece under 21. s. 4. d. 21. s. 6. d. 21. s. 8. d.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſty ſhall receive a hundred thouſand pounds in Silver, and not have a twenty ſhilling peece in Gold in a payment in the Exchequer. What is the reaſon the Merchants and Goldſmiths have made it a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize? they have againſt your Majeſties Lawes, to your weakning, and diſhonour, and againſt your Majeſties Imperial Crown, and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, robbed You, and the Kingdom, of all the Gold; broke your Royal Statutes and Proclamations, beggered your Majeſties Mint.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102645:8"/>
            <p>And theſe very men that have thus abuſed your Majeſty, after all this licentiouſneſſe, are ſo bold to deſire to ſteal one of the prime Flowers out of your Majeſties Crown.</p>
            <p>Which is by having an Act of Parliament, that they might freely, and at their will tranſport Gold and Silver, at their pleaſure; they will (if they could get this great power into their hands) leave neither Gold nor Silver in the Nation, but light and clip'd money, groats, ninepences, and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenpence-half-pennies; let this be but taken notice of, how the Merchants have robbed your Royal Father, your Majeſty, and the whole Kingdom, of the currant Gold of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And then I humbly leave it to your Majeſties wiſdom to conſider what a project this is, tending to the weakning of your Majeſty, and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Theſe men that have tranſported the Gold and Silver of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom already, without your Majeſties leave, and againſt the Law, are grown monſtrous rich many of them by tranſporting all the Gold of the Nation, and moſt of the Silver.</p>
            <p>And now their riches makes them ſo bold, thinking to bribe out all buſineſſe, as formerly they did in the Rump Parliament; they would work iniquity by a Law, if your Sacred Majeſty, or your privy Councellors ſhould ever permit them, to the ruine and damage of the whole Kingdom, to gratify the greedy avarice of ſome Merchants, whoſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe will never be ſatisfied; gain is their godlineſſe, and not god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe their gain.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſty, your Royall Grandfather, and Father, King JAMES and King CHARLES of bleſſed memory, gave a ſtop to this miſchief of tranſporting Gold, by bringing ſome of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>London,</hi> that tranſported Gold and Silver into forreign parts, into the <hi>Star Chamber</hi> in the years 1619. Sir <hi>William Curtine,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Vanlor,</hi> Mr. <hi>Delabar,</hi> Sir <hi>Moſes Trian,</hi> and ſome twenty more were fined in the <hi>Star Chamber</hi> at near two hundred thouſand pounds, and paid King JAMES into his Exchequer, for their compoſition, about one hundred thouſand pounds; this ſentence gave a ſtop to the tranſporters of Gold, and upon this ſentence, ſhortly after the Mint flouriſhed.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſties Royal Father, in the year 1635 King CHARLES of bleſſed memory, commanded me your Majeſties Humble and Loyall Subject, to diſcover all ſuch as tranſported Gold or Silver without His leave. I have the Kings Majeſties Gracious Letter to me of thanks for my good and acceptable Service, under His Majeſties Royal Hand and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102645:8"/> Signet, for diſcovering the tranſporters of Gold and Silver, which Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I have ready to produce to your Sacred Majeſty.<note place="margin">1648. On <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Braudgen</hi> brought me your Mrajeſties Royall Fathers command to put a charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of Gold in the Exchequer. Notwithſtanding his Majeſties for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer command to forbid me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of Gold 1643. becauſe his Majeſty heard that ſome Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliam. in 1648. was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding away their eſtates in Gold, he would have them diſcovered, and made known to the people how they robbed them of their Treaſure.</note> I cauſed the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of Gold at my own charge to be fined 24100 pounds, I cauſed upon command of his late Majeſty to be filed in the Exchequer in 1648, as will appear on Record at this day, above a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſeveral informations againſt the Tranſporters of Gold and Silver, at my charge many hundred pounds, I know the men and their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments at this day as well as I know my right hand from my left. I cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an exception, to have all the Tranſporters of Gold excepted out of the general pardon granted by the Parliament in the year 1651, as will appear in the Act, I put in an exception to have had it excepted in his Majeſties general pardon 1660, but there was ſo many guilty perſons that had tranſported Gold and Silver out of the Kingdom, that I could not get it put into the Bill to have theſe offences excepted, whereby your Majeſty loſt one hundred thouſand pounds, had I got it excepted out of your Majeſties pardon, there was above an hundred Merchants and Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths that I have proof againſt, for tranſporting Gold and Silver, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Kingdom of Millions of money; if your Majeſty pleaſe, I wil give your Privy Council a perfect liſt of their Names who tranſported Gold &amp; Silver, that ſhould have paid your Majeſty one hundred thouſand pounds, and thank God they eſcaped ſo too; I have all the charge againſt them, and the informations in the Exchequer is now on Record, and informations filed, to the juſt value of ſix hundred and fifty thouſand pounds.</p>
            <p>This buſineſs I acted, by command of his late Majeſty of bleſſed memory, and did lay out of my Purſe the ſum of nineteen hundred and ſixty pounds in diſcovery of the tranſporters of Gold in one thouſand ſix hundred thirty ſix, and had not your Majeſty pardoned the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, I would not for my ſhare have taken twenty thouſand pounds of them.</p>
            <p>I have it under your Majeſties Royal Fathers hand and ſignet from Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, that he would pay me for my great good and acceptable ſervice in diſcovering the tranſporters of Gold.</p>
            <p>This true account I humbly give your Majeſty, to ſhew there is no man in the Kingdom can diſcover the tranſporters of Gold ſo well as my ſelf; I know them as well as the Beggar knows his Diſh, and this is done by intelligence.</p>
            <p>I was for ſeven years commanded by his late Majeſty to give a ſtop to the tranſporting of Gold and Silver, and I did effect it, as appears by your Royal Fathers Letter, ready to be produced to your Majeſty.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102645:9"/>
                  <head>Here followeth your Majeſties Royal Fathers Letter verbatim, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>Charles R.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <p>TRuſtie and Wel-beloved, We Greet you well. Whereas We have formerly imployed you for the Diſcoverie of all ſuch as Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported Gold and Silver Coin beyond the Seas, and all ſuch likewiſe who contrarie to the Laws, and for their own private gain, have melted down great quantities of Silver; Wherein We acknowledg you did Us good and acceptable ſervice, for which (when God ſhall enable Us) We do hereby promiſe to give you full ſatisfaction. And for that We underſtand that you are preſſed by Our Two Houſes of Parliament to proceed in the ſaid Diſcoverie, We do hereby ſtrictly Command you that you intermeddle no further therein, without Our ſpecial Direction, As you will anſwer the contrarie at your peril. And for ſo doing, this ſhall bee your ſufficient Warrant. Given at Our Court at <hi>Oxford,</hi> the nineteenth day of <hi>November 1643.</hi> in the nineteenth year of Our Reign, &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By His Majeſtie's Command, GEORGE DIGBIE.</signed> To Our Truſtie and Well-beloved <hi>Thomas Violet</hi> Goldſmith in <hi>London.</hi>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102645:9"/>
            <p>If your Majeſtie will be pleaſed at this time to command me to Catch theſe <hi>Moles</hi> that work under ground, the Tranſporters of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and will Graciouſly Impower me with a Commiſſion, and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants to do the ſame, I will undertake to ſet your Majeſties Mint on work again, and ſtop the Tranſporting of Gold and Silver.</p>
            <p>Vaſt ſums of Mony is Tranſported daily, both Gold and Silver, which, if not in time prevented by your Majeſtie, and your Majeſties Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Prudent Councel, will weaken, and deſtroy your Majeſtie, and the Nobility, and the Commonalty in general, to make a few Merchants. If it be your Majeſties, and the Lords of your Councels pleaſure, to impower me to do it, I will (by Gods aſſiſtance) remove the obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Mint.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſtie, I ſhall humbly deſire, before any further progreſſe of this buſineſſe be made, concerning the giving the Merchants leave to tranſport Gold or Silver. That by your Majeſties eſpecial Command, a ſelect Committee of Merchants may meet, with ſome of the Officers of your Majeſties Mint, and my ſelf, and that we may be order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make a true Calculation of all Forreign Coins, both Gold and Silver, what every Coin will make, being its full weight, in the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> &amp; that we ſend for over from beyond the Seas Placcarts, Edicts, and Proclamations, of Forreign Countries; And that a Jury of Arteſts be commanded upon Oath, to make a true Report how they find Gold and Silver over valued in other Countries, and report as neer as they can the juſt and true Standard in Forreign Mints, what proportion they hold to the Mint of the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> When this is done, to conſider of what waies and means they uſe to keep their Mints on work, that ſuch waies as may be advantageous for ſetting your Majeſties Mint on work, may be obſerved to prevent former abuſes. That the waies and means how theſe Differences, Standards, may be rectified beyond Seas, and all Standards reduced to a pair, and equalitie with <hi>England,</hi> and this Miſterie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoulded truly to your Majeſtie after the eſſay by fire and water.</p>
            <p>And ſo when this buſineſſe, which is very weightie, is truly, and rightly ſtated by the Eſſay, Fineneſſe, and Weight, and is ſtrictly, and exactly ſtated to your Majeſtie, and your Privy Councel, then may it pleaſe your Majeſtie, by, and with the advice of your Privy Councel, ſuch waies may be concluded on, as your Majeſtie in your great wiſdom with advice of your Privy Council ſhall judge beſt for your ſervice.</p>
            <p>They being truly informed both by your judicious Merchants, and the Warden, Maſter, and Comptroller of the Mint, being aſſiſted with a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102645:10"/> Jurie of Arreſt to make Eſſay upon Oath. By this way I humbly ſay, the whole truth of this buſineſſe will be found out.</p>
            <p>The Law ſaith that Gold, and Silver, and Corne, and a mans Houſe is every mans own, to have a propriety in it to make uſe of between party and party, but not to deſtroy the propriety, but he is finable by the Law: a man cannot lawfully burn his own Houſe, burn his own Corne, Tranſport his own money, but it is finable; and this was uſed in the Star Chamber by the Atturny <hi>Banks,</hi> and the King's Councel at Law, as an Argument againſt the Tranſporters of Gold, in the Twelfth year of King CHARLES in the Star Chamber, when I proſecuted the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of Gold and Silver, by command of the late King CHARLES.</p>
            <p>I had disburſed in cauſing the Tranſporters of Gold and Silver to be fined in the Star Chamber 24200l. at my charge 1960l. and never as yet had penny for that ſervice. This very ſentence kept the Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in the Nation, till the beginning of the late War 1643. For which Service your Royal Father gave me thanks as aforeſaid, but as yet never had penny of Money for doing that Service.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſtie, whoſoever goes about to take the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative out of your Majeſties, and your Privy Councels hands, of hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the Tranſporting Gold and Silver without your Majeſties licence; I humbly ſay it is a Jeſuitical, Fanatick deſign, under the ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Freedom of Trade, to rob your Majeſtie, and your Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, of the priviledg of keeping in the Treaſure, and Wealth of this Kingdom, weakning your Majeſtie, and your Privy Councel, and your Royal Prerogative, leaving the Wealth, and Treaſure of this Kingdom, in Gold and Silver, to be guided by the covetous deſire of ſome Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, many of them care not two pence for the ſafety of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, ſo they, and their private Families grow rich. I humbly ſay it is a preſumptuous motion of ſome hot headed Merchants, that would by crafty and ſly pretences rob your Majeſtie of that which is next to the Militia of the Kingdom, nay, it is the very ſoul of the Militia, Gold and Silver; get to be Maſter of that, any man may get Shipping, Armes, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and any thing to make a diſturbance in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>We lately ſee upon what ſlie pretences the Sword was wrung out of your Majeſties Royal Fathers Hands; he that caſt his eye upon any of the Flowers of your Majeſties Imperial Crown, with intent to take them out either by fraud or force, let them fall as <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biram,</hi> and let their end be like <hi>Achitophels,</hi> who ſeek to rob your Royal Majeſtie of this your juſt Prerogative.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:102645:10"/>
            <p>And this I here humbly ſay, I will with my life maintain before your Majeſtie, and your Privy Councel, and the Parliament or Committee of Trade: And theſe following Statutes, Lawes and Proclamations are my Protection, and Warrant for what I humbly ſay.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Proclamation againſt giving for Gold, more then it is currant.</hi> 21. July. 17. Jacob.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A Proclamation against melting, and culling heavy Engliſh Money.</hi> 18. May. 9. Jacob.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Proclamation againſt buying and ſelling Gold and Silver at high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Priſes then the Mint.</hi> 14. May. 1. Jacob.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>A Proclamation againſt Tranſporting of Gold.</hi> 23. May 1. Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>A Proclamation againſt Profit for Gold and Silver; And melting.</hi> Engliſh <hi>Money. And to prevent the abuſes and waſt, in making Gold and Silver Threed, and Laces.</hi> 4. Feb. 3. Caroli.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>A Proclamation againſt Tranſporting Gold and Silver, and melting down the Currant Silver Coins of the Nation, for Plate, or Gold, or Silver Threed.</hi> 15. May. 3. Carolus.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſtie, to obſerve with what care the wiſdom of former Parliaments intruſted the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and their Privy Councel, to keep carefull watch that the Gold and Silver once import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into this Nation, ſhould be converted into Coin, for the Strength and Honour of the Kingdom; that thoſe that did Tranſport Gold and Silver without the King's Licence, were Felons. And in the Tryall in the Star. Chamber, 12. <hi>Caroli Primi,</hi> which I followed by Order of his late Majeſtie of bleſſed memory. The Atturney-General <hi>Banks,</hi> and the King's Councel, read many Preſidents, wherein the Tranſporters of Gold and Silver had judgment, and ſuffered execution of death, as Felons.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſtie will finde tranſporting Gold or Silver without the Kings licence to be Felony, and by ſeveral Acts of Parliament, 17 <hi>Edw.</hi> the 4. and the 4 <hi>Henry, cap.</hi> 13. And I humbly conceive the Kingdom is in as great ſcarcity of Gold and Silver now as it was then, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Gold and Silver is tranſported without the Kings licence by the diſturbance of the late War, and now ſome Merchants are grown ſo preſumptuous, that they would have an Act of Parliament to make it to be at the will of the Merchants to tranſport what Gold or Silver freely they pleaſe without licence from the King, it were better for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that theſe that go about to take this prerogative from the King,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102645:11"/> were blind, rather then the reſt of the Kingdom ſhould ever ſee that day theſe Merchants ſhould have their will, Stat. 9. <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3. againſt the tranſporting of Gold or Silver without the Kings licence, or the melting down the currant ſilver coin by Goldſmiths or others into plate Stat. 2. <hi>Hen. 4. cap.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>No perſon ought to preſume to tranſport Gold or Silver either in coin or bulion, upon pain of forfeiture of as much as they might, which I take to be lives and eſtates.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Henry 6. cap.</hi> 6. Upon a grievous complaint made in Parliament, That great ſums of gold and ſilver was tranſported without the Kings li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence out of this Kingdom, it was ordered and enacted, That no gold, or ſilver ſhould be tranſported out of the Realm, and becauſe it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the gold and ſilver is tranſported by Merchant aliens, it is order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the Mercheant aliens ſhall find ſecurity in the Chancery that they ſhall not tranſport the gold or ſilver monies out of the Kingdom upon pain of forfeiture of the ſum or value, and if any do contrary and that duly proved, his pledges ſhall pay the forfeiture, though the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſtranger be gone beyond the Seas: If this Law had been put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution this laſt twenty years, the Kingdom had had millions of gold and ſilver, which it is now robbed of, and the offenders are now grown ſo impudent to hope to get an Act of Parliament to rob the kingdom of all the gold and ſilver, as the greedy Merchant ſhall find and ſee his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to ſend away what gold and ſilver they pleaſe, without the Kings majeſty or his privy Councils licence for the future.</p>
            <p>18 <hi>Edw.</hi> the 4. No perſon to carry gold or ſilver, or jewels out of the kingdom upon pain of Felony.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. An Act made that whoſoever ſhall carry any gold or ſilver out of the Realm without the Kings licence, ſhall forfeit double the value.</p>
            <p>The 5th. and 6th. of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. An Act touching the exchange of gold or ſilver, that whoſoever gave more for gold or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, then it is or ſhall be declared by the Kings Proclamation, ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer impriſonment for the ſpace of a year, and make fine at the Kings pleaſure, the one moity to his Majeſty, and the other moity to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that ſhall ſeize the ſame, or will ſue for it by the Bill of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; were the Gold-ſmiths of <hi>London</hi> ſued on this Statute it would ruine moſt of them. Had not the Act of Oblivion pardoned them, but that gives them no licence or protection now at this day to act as they do, to ſell gold for 21 and 22 ſhillings for a Twenty ſhilling peice.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102645:11"/> Till this be remedied and the rule for the price of gold ſet by your Majeſtie, the Mint will never coin gold to any conſiderable quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity.</p>
            <p>If this deſire of the Merchants ſhould go on, the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> which in all Kings raigns abounded with gold and ſilver, and famous for their pound ſterlings, the true guide and meaſure of our monies will be put to uſe the Rooking tricks of the Bankers of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and other Commonwealths.</p>
            <p>Feed the people with a paper credit and the Merchants have all the peoples money; I beſeech your Majeſty to conſider of this monſtrous deſign and propoſals of the Merchants, ſhould by your Majeſty be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which God defend, in whoſe hands your Majeſty diſpoſeth the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of the kingdom, even truly your Majeſty would ſurrender the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia of the kingdom into the Merchants power.</p>
            <p>To ſend away all the treaſure of the kingdom, by which means, they will ſo fetter and impoveriſh the people of the kingdom, that when your Majeſties loving Subjects would give you aid by conſent of Parliament, they have no monies to do it but at the Merchants plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, who will be the onely Judges of the price they ſhall pay by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing, and the quantity in coin they will pleaſe to let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have.</p>
            <p>Should the Parliament now grant your Majeſty a paiment of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pounds in coined <hi>Engliſh</hi> gold, at twenty ſhillings the peice of gold, according to the Lawes and Statutes and your royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Proclamation, which forbids all either Forreigners or Natives whomſoever, to pay, give, or utter the currant coins of gold or ſilver at above the Kings proclamation, upon pain of forfeiture and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment during the Kings pleaſure. See the Statute law 5, 6, <hi>Edward</hi> 6. Yet for all your Maieſties lawes and proclamations, your Maieſty nor the Parliament ſhall not receive a hundred thouſand pounds in gold or a hundred pound, but at the Merchants price, <hi>viz.</hi> 21 ſhill. 4 pence, 21 ſhill. 6 pence, 21 ſhill. 8 pence, 22 ſhill. for a twenty ſhillings piece of gold. This is done in contempt of your Majeſty and the law, becauſe the Merchants have got all the coined gold into their hands, and tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to forraign parts, and they will not let it come back again but at their pleaſure and price make ſilver a free merchandize, the merchants will guide the prize and ſend it all away, to the deſtruction of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Mint.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102645:12"/>
            <p>The Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> had they this power they deſire, would by tricks, either by Security or Exchange, get all the Gold and Silver into their hands.</p>
            <p>And then I tremble to think what will follow, if the Merchants be Maſters of all the money: your Majeſties Fleet will lie at <hi>Chatham,</hi> at <hi>Portſmouth, &amp;c.</hi> and no moneys to be raiſed, but at the will of their Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; Your people in Parliament ſhall grant your Majeſties Subſidies, and when it comes to be paid, they have no money but what is in the Merchants Banks, or upon the Merchants Security, they having gotten into their hands all the money.</p>
            <p>All the world knows, the whole ſtock of the money of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is to be diſpoſed of by the credit of the City of <hi>London;</hi> the City of <hi>London</hi> gives the Rule to the Kingdom, and the Merchant of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> for credit upon money rules the City, now if your Majeſtie ſhould put this power into the Merchants hands, to tranſport Gold and Silver at their pleaſure, it would be a ready way to ſee the late Tragedies act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over again; and it is granted by all perſons, that Gold and Silver commandeth all things; if your Majeſtie ſhould part with this Royal Prerogative, I humbly deſire your Majeſtie, upon my knees, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider where you will lodge this great Jewel, which is the quinteſſence of the <hi>Mllitia:</hi> I humbly ſay many Merchants of <hi>London</hi> are recovered but lately out of the madneſs of a dangerous Rebellion, and wiſe men uſe to watch ſuch as have been once frenzie afterwards in all their actions, leſt being let goe at their own pleaſure they one time or another do either themſelves or ſome others a miſcheif; this I now humbly ſay, is to preſerve your Majeſties Greatneſs, Honour, and ſafety of your Majeſty, and your moſt honourable Privy Council.</p>
            <p>I ſtudy not to pleaſe ſome Merchants, but to ſerve your Majeſtie in truly ſtating this buſineſs, I being formerly imploied in this ſervice by your Royal Father he would have believed me in this point, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the regulating of Gold and Silver lace, and removing the obſtructions of the Mint for ſeven years, I had the onely care of this buſineſs by his Majeſties order, to prevent the tranſporting Gold or Silver.</p>
            <p>If your Majeſtie ſuffer the Merchants to obtain this their deſire, all the paiments of the Kingdom will be unfixed, and your Majeſties Subjects will have no money left but Groats, and ſome odd monies, to buy But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Eggs; the Tenants muſt pay their Rents after the Barbarious way in SCOTLAND, in Boules of Corne, and Chaldrons of Victualls, Coles, Horſes, Cowes, and Sheep. Your Majeſties Privy Councel,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102645:12"/> and your great Lords, and Gentry, muſt truck with their Tenants inſtead of a thouſand pound Sterling, to be paid them in current Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, according to 20. s. the pound Sterling for Gold, they muſt at this day pay 21. s. 6. d. if they will have a twentie ſhillings peece; is not this a wrong and dimunition to all the Lords in ENGLAND, ſeven pound ten ſhillings in the hundred, in all the Rents they are out of by Leaſe.</p>
            <p>But let Silver be made a free Merchandize, to Tranſport at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, without your Majeſties leave, farewell all Land-Lords payments in money (then, which God defend your Majeſtie ſhould expoſe all the Nobilitie to be at the will of the Merchants, for to receive either their Rent in Money or Ware.) All payments in Silver will raiſe the price of your Engliſh ſhilling ſhall be ſet againſt your Majeſties Crown, and Dignitie by the Merchant, as at this day, all the world know they have preſumed without your Majeſties leave, and againſt your Lawes, to ſend away all your Majeſties current Gold of the Nation, and to make it a Merchandize here in <hi>London,</hi> in contempt, deſpite, and affront of your Majeſtie, the Parliament, and your Majeſties Lawes and Statutes, and now are ſo brazen Fac'd, that they look, and ſue to have libertie to rob the King of this great priviledg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I humbly hope the Merchants bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daies are paſt, they had once a time in the long Parliament to make their Gold and Silver break thorough all Barrs, all Lawes; a Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>London,</hi> with a joynt Purſe, was ſuch a <hi>Roman</hi> Ram, that it batter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down all the Lawes, and Statutes. I humbly hope this buſineſſe, and the miſchiefs that would follow, if they ſhould obtain, their deſire is ſo clearly ſtated, to be only in your Majeſtie, and your moſt Honourable Privy Councel, that you will never part with it to any Corporation of Merchants, or others, but to keep it ſafe where the Law hath diſpoſed it, it is a Iewel the Law hath inveſted in the Crown, and cannot be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, it is an ineſtimable Pearl, and Riches.</p>
            <p>That if the Merchants could by confederation pay down a Million of Money to your Majeſtie preſently, to have it in their hands; Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie would be a loſer, Your Majeſtie would part with that which is Your Honour, Your Safetie, Your Lords, and all Your Peoples ſafetie, the Soul of the Militia.</p>
            <p>I pray God upon my Knees, your Majeſtie, and your Privy Councel, would conſider what is here ſaid, and ſet a mark on theſe men that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt under ſly and fained pretences, by ſubtiltie and craft, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your Majeſties Throne, Crown, and Dignitie; theſe men that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this to be in their Power, are like Water men, look one way, and Row another.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102645:13"/>
            <p>Theſe men many of them have deſigned in their heart the moddle of a Common-wealth, to be the fitteſt Government for this Kingdome; God hath delivered your Majeſtie from the Sword-man, the Club man, and hath reſtored your Majeſtie to the Glory, and Greatneſſe of your Royal Father, and your Predeceſſors, with the Hearts of all your good Subjects, and a large increaſe of the Revenues of your Crown, to the joy of all your Majeſties good Subjects.</p>
            <p>This Glory troubles ſome <hi>Mungrels</hi> of LONDON, that dare not bark, but are at this day cunning fauning <hi>Spaniels,</hi> that would by fauning co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen your Majeſtie of this Great, atd Royal Prerogative, which had they it, in ſeaven years they may lay ſuch a Foundation, that the Child un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born may rue it.</p>
            <p>I have read of a little Fiſh that ſticking to a Ships ſide ſhall ſtop a great Ship under ſail. The Merchants of a Kingdom or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth that are Bankers and have libertie to tranſport Gold and Silver at their pleaſure, rule the Commonwealth both for War or Peace, and have virtually the ſovereign power, being Maſters of all the peoples mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Theſe Bankers can hang a Pad-lock on the Commonwealths Sword when they pleaſe: God defend your Majeſtie and your Lords from ſuffering them to do ſo in your Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> for all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before and after following.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Merchants of London</hi> have tranſported all the Gold and moſt of the Silver out of <hi>England,</hi> principally by the confederation and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Goldſmiths in <hi>Lumbardſtreet,</hi> who are juſt in the nature of the Bankers at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and the Goldſmiths is your Merchants Jac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call as the Jac-call is to the Lion, they hunt for the Lions prey. The Goldſmiths lay up Gold and Silver for the Merchants to tranſport, ſome Goldſmiths in <hi>Lumbardſtreet,</hi> keeping at this day many great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>London</hi> caſhes, and ſome Noble mens caſh by this credit of ſeveral mens monies, the Goldſmiths in <hi>Lumbardſtreet</hi> are in the nature of Bankers, and have a great ſtock of Treaſure by them alwayes of Gold, forraign coines, and Silver.</p>
            <p>And as theſe and the Merchants pleaſe to truck and and chaffer, ſet the price of the currant Gold of your Kingdom at above the price cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by Proclamation of your Royal Father, and above the price of your Mint, to the deſtruction of your Majeſties Mint, and againſt your Crown and Dignities; your Majeſties Mint is tied to a certain rule both for the weight and fineneſs of the Standard of your Majeſties Gold and Silver, and cannot by the Law exceed; now here is the miſchief.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:102645:13"/>
            <p>The Goldſmiths they go between the Mint and the Merchants that tranſports Gold and Silver, and out-bids the Mint, 1. d. and ſometimes 2. d. and more the Ounce in Silver, and five ſhillings the Ounce in Gold at this day, and ſo catch up all the Gold and Silver to tranſport, being Factors, and Purveyors to the Merchants that tranſports Gold and Silver.</p>
            <p>And by this confederation between the Merchants, and Goldſmiths, contrary to the Lawes, and Proclamations of the Kingdom, they have cheated, and robbed the Kingdom, and your Majeſties Mint in the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and for theſe laſt fifteen Years have deſtroyed, and made deſolate the ſame.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſties Mint in all times, by the Law, ſhould have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, and firſt ſerved.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſties Mint at this day is neglected, your Majeſties Lawes deſpiſed, and your Majeſtie, and the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Lords, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Commons, cheated, and robbed of all your Gold, and almoſt all your Silver, to the weakning, and impoveriſhing of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>This wickedneſſe is done onely for the inriching of a few particular Perſons, Goldſmiths, and Merchants, to the deſtruction of the whole Kingdom, and if not timely prevented, to the ruine, and deſtruction, and decay of Trade. This was done when we had no KING in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God forbid your Majeſtie now ſhould ſuffer it.</p>
            <p>If your Majeſtie by your juſtice do not make ſome of theſe Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors an example, and timely prevent it, by the grave advice of your moſt Honourable Lords of the Councel for the time to come, to prevent theſe abuſes by a Law, or renewing the old Laws by your Majeſties Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, making it loſſe of Eſtate for any Goldſmiths to ſell any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Gold or Silver to tranſport, or to convert Gold or Silver into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other uſe then Plate, and Gold, and Silver Wyer, the Offendor for ever after to loſe his Freedom.</p>
            <p>And that no Merchant, or Goldſmith, ſhall give for Gold or Silver more then it ſhall be declared for by Proclamation, upon pain of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And that all Goldſmiths that are Exchangers of Forreign Bullion, ſhall enter into ſecuritie with the Officers of your Majeſties Mint, to your Majeſties uſe, to Coin the ſame, and to convert it to no other uſe. That no Merchant obtain a Licence from your Majeſtie, to tranſport Gold or Silver, nor the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Company, other, or more then they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cauſe upon their own proper accompt, to be truly imported, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Charter; and that all Warrants for tranſporting Gold
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102645:14"/> or Silver be Regiſtred, and the Goldſmiths to be tyed to Coin all the Gold and Silver they ſhall hereafter buy, ſuch Goldſmiths that will not to be debarred, the liberty to have power to exchange Forreign Gold and Silver, this being a Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of the Crown, and never granted the Company of the Goldſmiths, as I can prove by the Law, that the Warden of your Majeſties Mint is your Majeſties Exchanger, and he may Licence any whom he pleaſe to buy Forreign Bullion, provided they put in ſecuritie to Coin it in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and convert it to no other uſe but to coin upon the pain of forfeiture of his Bonds to your Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe Your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> my moſt humble prayer to Your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and Privy Councel is, that at this juncture of time the late Lord Cottingtons Rules &amp; Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations may be made uſe of for bringing of Gold and Silver into the Kingdom, that State-man about the year 1630. made a moſt advantageous Contract with the King of Spaine, for the bringing in Silver from Spaine in Engliſh, bottoms and Landing the Silver at Dover, one third part to be Coyned in Your <hi>Majeſtyes</hi> Royal Fathers Mint in the Tower of London, and the other two parts by Your <hi>Majeſtyes</hi> Royal Father, and his Privy Councels Licence to be tranſported at the will of the Importer, this Commiſſion was granted under the Great Seal of Your <hi>Majeſtyes</hi> Royal Father, by the advice of his Privy Councel, and above ten milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Silver Coyned upon that Contract, from the year 1630. to 1643. This Silver hath bin almoſt all tranſported away for the private profit of the Merchant, and little currant Silver Coyne left in the Kingdom, but light and eliped, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſet mony in abundance. All the Gold ſent away, to the deſtruction of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for the private profit of the Merchants. If Your <hi>Majesty</hi> pleaſe to inquire of Your Officers of the Mint they can certifie this is the truth. And what a dangerous Project this was of ſome men, to goe about to ſteal ſo Royal a Flower out of the Crown, ſuch pilferers are Enemies to Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Crowne and Dignity, and ought to be watched as men newly recovered out of a Lunacy, kept from doing either themſelves or others miſchefe.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> having peace with Holland, and France, will not have occaſion to Export ſo much Mony for Flanders, as He had when He had Wars with Them. Yet great Summes of Silver will dayly be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to Flanders from Spaine, to pay the Spaniſh Garriſons in Flanders, and the Trade from Spaine to Antwerp, to pay the Bankers there, will dayly cauſe great quantities of Silver to be Exported from Spain.</p>
            <p>I humbly deſire, that upon Treaty with the Spaniſh Ambaſſador, the Lords of the Councel would take order to Carry the King of Spaines Silver, as the Lord <hi>Cottington</hi> ſetled it; and that by the Law it ſhould be made Felony, for any Perſon that did not Coyne one full third part of all Silver that by agreement with the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhould be coyned, this Licence to be Canſtantly allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any Perſon upon the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Compoſition for Trade from <hi>Spaine;</hi> And for all other Perſons whomſoever, that Import Silver or Gold, to have it by Act of this Parliament, after the ſaid Silver is Landed, that any Perſon that Tranſports Gold or Silver, it ſhould be Confiſcation of Ship and Goods, and Impriſonment during the Kings pleaſure. Beſides, the Forfeiture of all Gold and Silver ſo put on Ship-board to Tranſport without Your Majeſties, or your Privy
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102645:14"/> Councels Licence; And that all Gold-ſmiths, or others whomſoever, that Culleth and Melteth down the Currant heavy Silver Coyns, for any Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, or to Tranſport, it ſhall be Felony, and that without Mercy.</p>
            <p>If Theſe Lawes by this Parliament be Revived, and I your Majeſties Loyal Subject Impowered, and Commanded by your Majeſties Moſt Honourable Privy Councel, to See to the due Execution of them; By the Bleſſing of God, I wil in a few Yeares Repleniſh the Great want, and Scarcity of Gold and Silver, in the Kingdom againe; And Remove the preſent Obſtructions of the Mint.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſtie, It is the Execution of the Law quickens and gives life to the Law, when knowing perſons ſhall be intruſted to ſee to the Execution.</p>
            <p>There are Laws and Proclamations againſt tranſporting gold, but no incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement conſiderable for a mans time, all the Laws in the world will never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this abuſe, if ſome Truſty perſons be not appointed to look in a particular manner, and make it their buſineſs, and a man cannot imploy ſeveral people to do this ſervice but at great charge, vigilance and diligent attendance to keep his watches, and intelligence in <hi>London,</hi> and the Ports; this miſchief daily increaſes, becauſe no knowing perſon is impowred and commanded to take care of this great buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> would not admit the <hi>Eaſt India Company,</hi> at her firſt grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be a Corporation, to tranſport the King of <hi>Spains</hi> ſilver coin into the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> though the Merchant preſſed it very often; telling her Majeſty that her Silver Coin and Stamp was not known in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> they think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by that to get a Licenſe to ſend what Silver they pleaſed: This moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Queen, and her wiſe Privie Councel replyed, to the Merchants of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, that for the very reaſon the Merchant alledged, to tranſport the King of <hi>Spains</hi> ſilver to the <hi>Eaſt Indies;</hi> It was her fixed reaſon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution unalterable, ſhe would not grant the <hi>Eaſt India Company</hi> leave to ſend the King of <hi>Spains,</hi> or any forreign Princes coin into <hi>India,</hi> but ſuch Silver as was coined with her Effigies and Picture on the one ſide, and the Percullis on the other ſide, of the juſt weight and fineneſs of the Spaniſh peeces of eight, and peeces of four Royals, and no other Silver ſhould by her Merchants be ſent to <hi>India.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this was her Majeſties prudent reaſon for the doing thereof, that becauſe the <hi>Indians</hi> did not know her, nor ſee her greatneſs on her Silver, her Majeſty gave the <hi>Eaſt India Company</hi> leave to tranſport Gold or Silver, but ſo as ſhe would for the time to come give them a juſt occaſion to reverence and honour her, and bow at her <hi>Effigies,</hi> declaring ſhe would all the world over, where ſhe gave her Merchants leave to Trade, be known to be as great a Prince as the King of <hi>Spain:</hi> And that none ſhould preſume to ſend a greater quantity of Silver then ſhe in her wiſdome ſhould judge fit, to the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> as will appear by their Charter, both for the quantity, and with her <hi>Figure, Motto,</hi> and <hi>Percullis</hi> upon the Silver: The Queens Majeſty declaring ſhe held it as a ſpeciall and chief Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of her Crown and Dignity to put the <hi>Percullis</hi> upon all the Silver the <hi>Eaſt India Company</hi> ſhould ſend to the <hi>Indies:</hi> Nor would ſhe admit the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the <hi>Eaſt India Company</hi> to ſend more Silver then ſhe and her Privie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102645:15"/> Councel did approve of; as appears in the Journal Books, the yearly Licences de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring ſhe would have her Merchants in that point to be ſubordinate to her will, not her will to be ruled at the Merchants pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And ſo during all her proſperous Reign to her death, this great and prudent Queen ruled her Merchants, and not the Merchants her; this was according to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> the Queen would ever be known to be a Queen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Narrative will appear to be true, by the Stamps, Weights, and Standard of this Silver that was coyned in the Tower ready to be produced to your Majeſty, and the moſt Honourable Privie Councel, if your Majeſty require the ſame; this courſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all Queen</hi> Elizabeths <hi>Reign, and it would be for the honour and greatneſs of your Majeſty, that all Silver tranſported to the</hi> Indies <hi>ſhould be coyned of the weight of Pieces of Eight, with your Majeſties Royall Effigies, and the</hi> Percullis <hi>in the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>that ſo all the world over, the Nations might ſee your Royal ſtamp, and bow down, and do reverence; What an honour had it been to your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Grandfather and Father to have had ſixty hundred thouſand pounds tranſported in Silver to the</hi> Indies, <hi>with their ſtamp; which would have been done had Q.</hi> Elizabeths <hi>honourable Rule been obſerved: I humbly deſire it may be done hereafter, though your Majeſtie get nothing but fame, no profit. I dare undertake the</hi> Eaſt India <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall have their ſilver coined in the Tower for 12 pence the pound weight, that is 60000 l. coyned for one thouſand pounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Eaſt India Company <hi>by monie got this Royal Priviledge laid down at the beginning of King</hi> James <hi>his Reign, to the great impairment and loſſe of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial royal Crown and Dignity; and to the great loſſe of his Majeſty in his Mint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Coynage and the loſing and diminution of your Royal Grandfather and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Bleſſed memory, in their Revenue at this day above an hundred thouſand pounds in the total ſum in the duty of coyning, there being ſince</hi> King James <hi>his Reign by that Company above ſixty hundred thouſand pounds in Silver and Gold ſent to the</hi> Eaſt Indies, <hi>were their Books of Entries examined, and their Books of Account to their ſeveral Factories in</hi> India; <hi>what they have ſent yearly to every particular factory, and ſome Auditors appointed to make the inſpection upon Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I humbly ſay, there would be found many hundred thouſand pounds tranſported both of Engliſh Gold, and Silver, more then ever they had licence from the King to ſend to the great weakning, damage and decay of this Nation, they being a Company that heretofore uſed to bribe out all their abuſes by one courſe or other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Had not your Majeſty by your Royal pardon pardoned them, they ſhould before this time have found the</hi> Eaſt India <hi>Company charged by me in the Exchequer with many hundred thouſand pounds of Engliſh Gold and Silver, and of half Crowns and foreign Gold and Silver tranſported, againſt the Laws and Statutes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, let them have got off as well as they could.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe your Majeſty, That company pretends a debt your Royal Father ſhould owe them for Silks and Pepper delivered unto one</hi> Burlemack, <hi>a Merchant, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Year, 1630. upon your Royal Fathers account, had not your Majestie in your great mercy pardoned this very Company of Merchants in your gracious and free Pardon, 1660. I could have chalked out the way to have peppered the</hi> Eaſt India
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102645:15"/> 
               <hi>Company, it had never been ſo peppered ſince it was a Company, they are pardoned for what is paſt, but they have no Priviledge for the time to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if your Majeſty command me to watch the</hi> Eaſt India <hi>Company that they for the future ſend no more gold or ſilver then they have licence for from your Majeſty; I ſhall faithfully do it, and give a ſtop to theſe miſchiefs they have formerly committed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If your Majeſty command, I ſhall not fear the riches or greatneſs of the</hi> Eaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia <hi>company, or Merchants of</hi> London, <hi>but I will tramel them and reduce them to the due obedience of your Majeſties commands, and the Law of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the longer this buſineſs is not looked after, makes ſome Merchants think to get leave to weaken the Kingdom in general, and incroach upon your Majeſties ſacred Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to ſend what ſilver and gold they liſt away for the future, without any Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe your Majeſty,</hi> a Court in the nature of the Star chamber, would Froſt-bite theſe Gentlemen, and make them pluck in their Horns, and ſubmit to your Maieſties Lawes, which will be for the good of the Nation in general, that theſe men may be curbed, and not left to rob the Kingdom of all its Gold and Silver, as ſome Merchants have taken the boldneſs to do, when we had no King in this our <hi>Iſrael</hi> for this laſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen years.</p>
            <p>Never <hi>School-boyes</hi> plaid ſuch tricks in the abſence of their <hi>School-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> as ſome of the <hi>London-merchants</hi> have done: When the books of the Common council of <hi>London,</hi> copied out together with the Eaſt <hi>India</hi> Companies books, be throughlie inſpected, your Maieſtie and your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privie Council will ſee incredible paſſages, fit for Your maieſtie to know, ſuch as is for Your maieſties honour and ſafetie for the future to prevent, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I moſt humbly pray your Majeſtie and your honourable Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, to command true Copies of all the Acts of the Common Council of <hi>London,</hi> from one thouſand ſix hundred and thirty eight, to one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and ſixty, and the true copies of the Eaſt Indies Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies books of Envoys ſent to their Factors, of all the Gold and Silver they ſent yearly, the ſhips name, and by what Factor, and to what Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> ever ſince one thouſand ſix hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty: Not that I have the leaſt thought that any of them ſhould be puniſhed for what is paſt, by reaſon of your Majeſties gracious pardon, but that an Eye might be kept over them to keep them from committing the ſame or the like offences again againſt your Majeſtie, your Crown, and Dignity.</p>
            <p>I humbly ſay, I am ſo charitable to them, that I had rather ſee them
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102645:16"/> alwaies upright in all their actions, then ever to hear that your Majeſtie ſhould put your Royal ſelf to that trouble to pardon them again; when they have offended, it is better, I humbly ſay, for the Merchants, that your Majeſty take all courſe to keep ſome Merchants from falling; then to take them up after they are down, if they be watched that they ſhall have no opportunitie to offend, it ſaves the labour of puniſhing any of them.</p>
            <p>Some Merchants I have heard ſay at the Council of Trade one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and fiftie, that it is an old Hereſie to hinder the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of gold and ſilver freelie, and to retain it in the Kings hands he only to give a licence to tranſpor: Sure I am it is a Phanatick opinion for the Merchants to labour to obtain it out of your Majeſties and your privie Councils hands.</p>
            <p>Some Merchants are great magnifiers of Commonwealths, their Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Governments, thoſe that are for an <hi>Amſterdam model</hi> both in the Church and Kingdom; but in our Kings ſacred hands this great Truſt in all Ages hath happilie continued, and no Merchant never durſt ask ſuch a requeſt to have it at their own diſpoſe; theſe Merchants covet more profit and gain then they do the Kings Majeſties greatneſs, and that makes them ſo buſie to get this Royal flower out of the Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe your Majeſty,</hi> your standard of Gold and Silver is fixed to all your Subjects of all your Nations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the pound ſterling is a fixed paiment, and is the guide to all the Bankers in <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> for till they return their Bills of Exchange for <hi>England,</hi> no Banker or Merchant can tell certainly the true intrinſecal value they ſhall receive for a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds delivered in their Banks, by Bills of Exchange to any place but onely <hi>England,</hi> where theſe paiments are fixed and paied ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the pound ſterling, which is by ſhillings, pence, and half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, without any fraud or bankmonie, from the paiment of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound, to the paiment of one hundred thouſand pounds, no man can be wronged of a penie, but it will exactlie appear upon the caſting up of the accompt. Commonwealths and Bankers go upon Merchants ſubtilties, that is not for the Honour and Dignitie of your Majeſtie, to make your monie go high, when you are to paie your Armies and Fleets, and then preſently to call it down in Kingdomes; <hi>Kings are Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and cannot act ſuch dirty tricks,</hi> as Commonwealths do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands Tragedy</hi> from one thouſand ſix hundred fourtie three, to one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixtie, may ſerve as a warning to all good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102645:16"/> how to turn Kingdomes into Commonwealths, or to leave power of tranſporting Gold or Silver at the will and pleaſure of the merchant. Merchants are like fire and water, <hi>Good Servants, but bad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters;</hi> in their proper ſpheers good, but to get a head deſtructive to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; witneſs the late horrible <hi>Tragedies</hi> fomented and continued onely by the pleaſure and power of the Merchants and the wealth of <hi>London: The burnt Child dreads the fire.</hi> I loſt twentie thouſand pounds by the late Rebellion, which was hatched and kindled for the greateſt part by thoſe of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ſurfeited with Plenty, Riches, and Trade, the late Royall King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, by his late Royall Fleets, laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Merchants of <hi>Londons</hi> greatneſs and reputation all over the World, no Prince nor Commonwealth daring to injure the Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> but the King with the firſt winde had his Royal Fleets in their Harbours to demand reparation to the Merchants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, elſe their harbours debarred Trade<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The late glorious King got the envy of the Ship monies; but never a penny of it in his Exchequer. The Merchants of <hi>London</hi> got the profit, advantage, and ſecurity by Trading ſafely, and the Seas ſcoured from Pyrates: How unthankfully the Merchants required his Majeſty, was ſhown in this late Rebellion. I ſpeak not this that any ſhould be puniſhed, but that they might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented for the future to do the ſame things again, as they did this laſt ſeventeen years.</p>
            <p>In King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> their raigns, thoſe good Kings was got into the Citie of <hi>Londons</hi> debt, and to come out of it they did part with their Lands at half the value. When Maſters borrow Money of their Servants, it makes them generally overvalue themſelves and ſlight their Maſters. I hope in a few years his Majeſty will be in that condition to lend the City of <hi>London</hi> money, upon their Charter, the like to the Eaſt <hi>India</hi> Company and other Companies to have their Lands bound. This was King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſevenths way, he would alwaies have his Exchecquer full of money, finding it to be the greateſt ſecurity to prevent all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, to have the King richer then his people.</p>
            <p>In the year one thouſand ſix hundred fourty ſeven, your Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being informed that many Members of Parliament, and factious Citizens was tranſporting and packing away their eſtates in Gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, which theſe had in aboundance cozened the Kingdom of, your Royal Father commanded me by one Mr. <hi>Francis Brogdou,</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Gentleman, on whom his Majeſty conſtantly imploied to go between him and his loyal Subjects, then Priſoners in the Tower:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102645:17"/> This Mr. <hi>Francis Brogden</hi> brought me his Majeſties, your Royal Fathers pleaſure, that I ſhould labour in the pretended Parliament-houſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a commiſſion to diſcover the tranſporters of Gold and Silver, but ſo that if I obtained it, I ſhould uſe my diligence to diſcover the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-men, and their factious Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> to make them odious to the Kingdom that tranſported Gold and Silver out of the Nation: I uſed my endeavour to make them publick to the World, for ſeveral years, to get this Commiſſion to paſs by the pretended Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and it is well known to many of the then Parliament, Sir <hi>James Harrington, Fleetwood,</hi> and ſeveral others; but was particularly oppoſed by both the <hi>Aſhes, Allen, Harvey,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Vane, Strickland,</hi> and many others of the Parliament, and by ſwarms of Sectaries of the City of <hi>London:</hi> which men had tranſported the Gold and Silver out of the Nation; and therefore to be ſure to have them within compaſs of the Law, I cauſed a Gentleman to file in the Exchequer a hundred informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the tranſporters of Gold and ſilver, and to let them remain on record, till your Majeſties Royal Father did come to <hi>London</hi> (this was about one thouſand ſix hundred and fourty eight) at that time being the hopes and prayers of all good men. But God had decreed it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, by taking your Royal Father out of this World, the World eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, this unthankful Nation, not being worthy of him; ſo all things reſted till your Majeſties happy arrival in <hi>May</hi> 29. 1660.</p>
            <p>Concerning the tranſporting of Gold and ſilver, though your Majeſtie hath pardoned the tranſporters of Gold till 29. May 1661. I humbly ſay, your Majeſty hath declared that for the future you will have all men conformable to your Laws, without reſpect of perſons, if this rule be ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly obſerved, your Majeſty will never put this great buſineſs of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Gold and Silver to be at the Merchants will and pleaſure, leaſt the ſame tumults and troubles be played over again by ſome Phanatick Merchants, as they have done within twenty years; your Majeſty may as ſafely put a Sword into a Madmans hand, or a Knife into a Childs, as truſt the Merchants to tranſport Gold or Silver without your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties licence, after it is once landed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102645:17"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS moſt Excellent Majeſtie: And to the moſt Honourable the LORDS of his MAIESTIES moſt Honourable <hi>PRIVY CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCEL.</hi> The Humble Petition of <hi>THO. VIOLET</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Goldſmith.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt Dread Soveraign!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Your Majeſties moſt Humble and Loyall Subject for your Majeſties ſervice humblie pray, that the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> and <hi>Perſia</hi> Companie, bring in their Charter, whereby your Majeſtie and your Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Councel will inform your ſelves, by the Charter your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Father and Grand-Father paſſed with what priviledge they have granted them, &amp; upon what conditions and reſtrictions.</p>
               <p>2. That your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel would be pleaſed to require an accompt of the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> and <hi>Perſia</hi>-Companie, of all the ſummes of monie, Gold or Silver, either Forrain or Engliſh, which they have ſent into <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> ever ſince <hi>July</hi> 1620. this is no new thing, for they did in 1620. give an accompt, and made it by their Books appear, that from the Originall and firſt foundation of their Trade, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1601, to <hi>July</hi> 1620. they had ſhipped awaie for <hi>India</hi> onelie, <hi>548090l.</hi> ſterling in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> monies, and ſome <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102645:18"/> and <hi>Germane</hi> Dollars, which accompt was preſented in Parliament at that time.</p>
               <p>3. Your Petitioner deſires your Majeſty to take notice, that if the State in Parliament were then ſo carefull in times of peace, and the Trade of the Nation flouriſhing, to call the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Company to an accompt for twentie years, and to cauſe them to make their accompts plainly to appear by their Books for twentie years; ſurely, I humbly conceive, your Majeſties and your Privy Councell will exſpect for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Kingdom, to have an exact accompt of all the Treaſure the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> and <hi>Perſia</hi> Companie have exported; and to have them to Produce a juſt accompt, what quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Gold or Silver they have bought in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in other Forrein places, immediately upon their proper accompt; and what quantitie of <hi>Engliſh</hi> melted Silver in Bars, they have bought of Gold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſmiths in <hi>London;</hi> what quantities of Gold in Bars, they bought of the <hi>Guinie</hi> and <hi>Barbarie</hi> Companies, what quantities of <hi>Engliſh</hi> coined Gold they have ſent into the Eaſt-<hi>Indies,</hi> and to <hi>Perſia;</hi> what quantities of Cardques, Rix-Dollars, Rials of <hi>Spain,</hi> or any other Forrein Silver, they have bought up in <hi>London,</hi> of Merchants, Goldſmiths, or others, which without the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Company ſo buying, would have been brought into the Mint and coined, to the great augmentation of the ſtock of this Nation. And that they be required to give your Majeſty, and your Privie Councel, an Accompt of what quantity of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Piſtollets, <hi>Dutch</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>Hungarian</hi> Duckets, Gold <hi>Gilders,</hi> Gold <hi>Albertus</hi> of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Italian</hi> Piſtolets, <hi>Turky</hi> Sultels, and all other Forrein Gold and Silver, they have bought up in <hi>London,</hi> of Goldſmiths, Merchants, Natives, and Strangers, which have not been
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102645:18"/> members of their Companie, and tranſported to <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> ſince 1620. All which, I am ſure they have perfect Accompts of. And that the aforeſaid Companie be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſend your Majeſtie, and your Privie Councel, in all the Warrants and Licences for their doing of the ſame, and for a true diſcoverie of the premiſſes.</p>
               <p>4. That your Majeſty, and your Privie Councel, would require the Books of Envoies, of the ſame Lading of everie ſhip, of all the Gold and Silver, in Bars, or Coin, that bath been ſent to the Eaſt-<hi>Indies</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> ſince 1620. for by them your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel ſhall ſee what Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver each ſhip carried, and the Ships, Factors, and Maſter's names, and to what Factorie in <hi>Perſia</hi> or <hi>India,</hi> and the ſeveral years, and ſo your Majeſtie and your Privie Councell will quicklie ſee the juſt quantitie to a pennie what they have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and in what ſort of Coin, either Engliſh Gold or Silver, or Forrein Gold or Silver, for theſe fourtie years; the giving your Majeſtie and your Privie Councell a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt thereof, will be of great concernment to the Kingdom in many reſpects.</p>
               <p>5. That your Majeſtie and your Privie Councell would appoint a Committee to view over the Journal Books: for out of them there will be gathered buſineſſes of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Nation; and if ſome able Book-Keepers be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed with me, to take out what I ſhall obſerve in them, it will tend highly to the ſervice of your Majeſtie and give a ſtop to great miſchefs that is daily practiſed on the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>6. If your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel pleaſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your ſelves by this waie, your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel will ſee clearlie manie other ſecrets, upon peruſal of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102645:19"/> theſe Books, then I will ſpeak of, and ſo your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel will be able to rectifie and ſettle the Trade in a flouriſhing condition, that it may be benificiall to the Kingdom, and all the Adventurers, whereas heretofore, and now as it is managed, none getteth by it, but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of the ſaid Companies, and the Companies Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and their Officers. The Adventurers having been blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ever ſince it was a Companie, and led by the noſe by their ſervants, or elſe how could their Factors and ſervants be ſo rich, and the Companie's ſtock ſo poor.</p>
               <p>7. May it pleaſe your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel, I humblie conceive, upon the Examination of all the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, When that the Books of the Companie are examined, it will be found that the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Companie hath ſent awaie the Kingdoms Coin, both in Gold and Silver, manie hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pounds more then ever they had warrant for to do; from your Majeſties Grand-Father or Father, though your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel hath forgiven it, yet It ought to be prevented for the future this miſchief; which your Petitioner moſt humblie praies for your Majeſties and your Privie Counſels ſervice, alſo That your Majeſtie and your moſt honourable Privie Councel command a true Tranſcript under the hand of the Town-Clerk of the Citie of <hi>London;</hi> to be tranſmitted to your Majeſtie and your Privie Councel, of all the Acts, and Orders of the Common Councel from the year 1638. to the 25. <hi>March</hi> 1660. It is true, your Majeſtie by your gratious pardon hath pardoned all offences, but for the future there will be great uſe made of their Orders, to know by what degrees, and ſteps the late confuſions got to a head, and poiſoned that great bodie of your Citie of <hi>London;</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:102645:19"/> I humblie ſaie, your Majeſtie and your moſt honourable Privie Councel will make great uſe of the ſight of them, to prevent anie the like diſturbance again and to nip them in the bud (this will be for the generall good and quiet of the whole Kingdom) for as <hi>London</hi> pipes, ſo the greateſt part of the Kingdom dances, eſpeciallie all Cities and corporations, keep the ſpring head clear from being diſturbed, the ſtreams will run alwaies clear, they have your Majeſties moſt gratious pardon for what is paſt, but that gives them no priviledge to act the like things again, eitherby fraud, feined pretences, or by force.</p>
               <p>The Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Companie formerlie having made it their common practice by giving great ſummes of monie for Bribes, to have libertie to oppreſs the good people of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to have Licence with Authoritie to deceive the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; all which abuſes, I praie God, by the wiſdom of your Majeſtie, and your moſt honourable Privie Councel, may be carefullie found out, and ſuch Order and Regulation made for the future for all Traders, as may be moſt for the proſperitie of this Kingdom in generall, without anie regard to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt, when it ſhall be found deſtructive to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and your dutifull and loyal Subject ſhall pray for your Majeſties long and proſperous Reign over us.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Novemb. 28. 1660</date>.</dateline> Signed,
<signed>Tho. Violet.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:102645:20"/>
               <p>I charged the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company before the Councel of Trade, 1650. with robbing the Nation of many hundred thouſand pounds of Gold and Silver, more then they had Licence to ſend; and ſeverall other Miſdemeanours. Thereupon the Councel of Trade made theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="legal_document">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>Die Mercurii Sept. 11. 1650.</date> At the Councel for Trade at <hi>White-hall.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Ordered,</p>
                     <p>THat the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Company be deſired to produce their Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Charter before this Councel.</p>
                     <p>Ordered,</p>
                     <p>THat the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Company be deſired to bring into this Councel, what Licences they formerly have had granted them for the Tranſporting of Bullion, or Coin, ſince the year 1620.</p>
                     <p>Ordered,</p>
                     <p>THat the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Company be intreated likewiſe to produce the direct and true. Accompts of all the ſeverall ſummes of Bullion and Coin, in any ſpecie to the full, that hath been year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſported by them, ſince the year 1620.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Ex. Ben. Worſly, Secret.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>But theſe Orders were never obeyed, but ſome of the Rump Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was brib'd, and no Reformation, I only got the Envy for making
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102645:20"/> this Diſcovery, I humbly hope the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Companies time of bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing out all Buſineſs is expired, now in your Majeſties bleſſed Reign; Truth ſhall prevaile, eſpecially ſuch as are for your Majesties Honour, and Safety.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>I ſhall humbly ſhew your Majeſtie the damage the Kingdom ſuffered by ſending all the Silver to the Eaſt-<hi>Indies</hi> in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> monie, before it was coined with King <hi>Jame's,</hi> and King <hi>Charle's</hi> Face, and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culliſſes, as it was coined in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly recommend it to your Majeſtie, and your Privy Councel, to have all Silver ſo coined before it goes to the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is for the Greatneſs, and Honour of the King, to have the Silver, his Merchants Trade with, firſt coined with the Perculliſes, and His Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figies and Motto, all over the World; For the Kings greatneſse is the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſecuritie, and protection, and to be made of the weight of peices of Eight, and of the ſame Standard, as it was in the Queens time; the King loſes in point of Coinage by not Coining, the Silver is ſent to the Eaſt-<hi>Indies,</hi> as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did, the Eaſt <hi>India</hi> Companie had paid to the Kings Grandfather, and Father of bleſſed memory, a hundred thouſand pounds, which would have bin clear profit ſince King <hi>James,</hi> in his Majeſties Exchequer, and all his Officers for Coining payd, if Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Rule had been obſerved, to Coin all the Silver ſent beyond Seas. If the Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Companie Books be looked over, they have ſent above ſixtie hundred thouſand pounds in Silver to the Eaſt-<hi>Indies,</hi> ſince the firſt of King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Silver, more monie by farre then is at this day in <hi>England.</hi> I humbly recommend it for your Majeſties Honour and Profit that your Majeſtie for the future may coin all Silver, or Gold, that ſo the <hi>Indian</hi> Princes may ſee your Effigies, and bow at the ſight thereof; As Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> made the Merchants to do, or elſe they ſhould not ſend her Silver. The true ſafetie and protection of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102645:21"/> the Merchant is, that they are Subjects of ſuch a great King, that can cauſe Juſtice and Right to be done to His Merchants, as far as the Seas ebbs and flowes round about the World, it is truly for the Merchants ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie if they would conſider rightly of all things, and love the King's Honour, as well as their own Profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>MAY it pleaſe your Sacred Majeſtie, I here humbly give your Majeſtie, and your Privy Councel an accompt concerning my ſtaying the Ships <hi>Sampſon, Salvador,</hi> and St. <hi>George, 15. Decemb. 1652.</hi> The day the Judges had reſolved in the Admiraltie to clear theſe Ships, their Silver and Lading, there being three hundred thouſand pounds in them. I ſaw about that time <hi>Don Aſonſo Decar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denis</hi> the Spaniſh Ambaſſador Extraordinary, come to the Rump Parliament, and owned their power, as a free State and Parliament. I heard that many in <hi>Amſterdam</hi> was playing the ſame prancks there with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as the Londoners had plaied with Your Majeſties Royal Father, and your Majeſtie, I ſaw the Face of all things look very ſadly, both in <hi>France, Holland</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> the Royall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie being baniſhed from home, put to great extremities abroad, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inſufferable wants: At which time I had advice from one of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> that the three hundred thouſand pounds in Silver in the aforeſaid Ships, part of it appertained to <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Merchants, and other parts to <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and ſome to <hi>Hamburgers;</hi> and I had the Copies of the Original Commiſſion under the Great Seal of <hi>Holland,</hi> to <hi>de Witt,</hi> and <hi>de Ruter,</hi> the Vice Admirals of <hi>Holland,</hi> to require them to guard all Ships coming from <hi>Spain</hi> to <hi>Oſtend,</hi> or <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> and Parliament being at Warre; and this was done upon the Petition of the Merchants of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to the high and mightie Lords the States, to guard the Ships from the <hi>Engliſh;</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:102645:21"/> which Commiſſion, and Petition at this day remains in the Admiraltie. I caſt about how I might firſt divide the pretended Councel of State, in <hi>Decemb. 1652.</hi> amongſt themſelves, about this Silver, in the aforeſaid Ships, and ſet them to ſtay it, which I knew would ingage the Rump Parliament in a forreign War, and ſo though the Kings Partie were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed at home, the Rump might waſt their Souldiers, and have more hands about their Ears then they were aware of, and in time be beaten out of breath, and ſo the Royal Partie might riſe again. I divided the Councel ſo as there was ten for ſending me to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and clearing the Silver, and twelve for the ſtaying the Silver, and giving me thanks. I made ſome of my ſecret Friends acquainted with this deſign, they approved thereof; and ſo having promiſed ſecretly one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, for it concerned my life. I told them from time to time how I laid my deſign, till at laſt <hi>I</hi> ingaged <hi>Cromwel</hi> to take up the Silver from aboard the Ships, <hi>Sampſon, Salvador,</hi> and St. <hi>George,</hi> and that he would diſsolve the Parliament; the ſame night that he diſsolved the long Parliament, he could not ſleep for it about the 15. <hi>April 1652. Cromwel</hi> ſent <hi>Mr Sadler</hi> the Town-Clerk of LONDON, and Coll<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Bingham</hi> to me, to come preſently to him at the <hi>Cock-pit,</hi> to give him the Coppies of all the Bills of theſe Ships Lading, and the value of the Silver, which I did; and after he had them, <hi>Cromwell</hi> could not ſleep till he had the Silver in <hi>Bark ſteads</hi> cuſtody in the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> I found him to be forward in it, to get the Silver into his poſſeſion in the <hi>Tower,</hi> being 29. <hi>April 1653. Oliver Cromwell</hi> ſent a guard of Souldiers to ſeize on the Silver aboard theſe Ships, the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon, Salvador,</hi> and St. <hi>George,</hi> the 20. day of <hi>April 1652. Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi> tore his Hair before me, and a Friend of mine, <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> telling him that <hi>Cromwell</hi> had undone them all by forcing the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and that now he ſaw apparently he was an undone man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> ſtorming at me <hi>Tho. Violet,</hi> ſaying, I was the fatalleſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102645:22"/> man that ever was to the Councel and Parliament for ſtaying this Silver, and that had I not ſet the Councel and Parliament to ſtay this Silver, till that every mans claim was particularly proved, the Silver had been all Tranſported, and <hi>Cromwell</hi> never durſt have diſſolved the Parliament, had he not got the Silver in theſe Ships, being three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pounds into his hands.</p>
               <p>All which I did premeditately to ſet them, and the Councel, Parliament, and altogether by the Ears, to divide and weaken their Councels. And I made ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons acquainted with my deſign, who are wel known to your Majeſtie, both for their Service and Fidelity, if I be required I will name them. Before ever I undertook this Buſineſſe, I had their advices, and approbation under ſecreſie, for it had coſt us all our lives had it bin known, I had given the Parliament this vomit to undo them.</p>
               <p>This I can prove to be the truth, and Sir <hi>James Harrington, Frances Allen,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Scot</hi> uſed to ſay, it was <hi>Violet</hi> deſtroyed the Parliament, and not <hi>Cromwell;</hi> for had I not ſtayed the Silver <hi>Cromwell</hi> durſt not have forced the Parliament. But whereas Doctor <hi>Walker,</hi> and ſome others have declared to ſome Merchants, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <hi>London,</hi> I ſtayed the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Silver, and would not conſent to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge; I was ſo far from hindring the <hi>Spaniards</hi> of their right, that I Petitioned <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councel to diſcharge the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Silver. But Doctor <hi>Walker</hi> oppoſed me in it, as appears by Doctor <hi>Walkers</hi> Certificate to <hi>Cromwells</hi> Councel.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Jeſſop</hi> Clerk of the Parliament delivered it to me upon condition I ſhould return it to him when I had done with it, I humbly pray your Majeſties moſt Honourable Councel to take the pains to peruſe it, and they will ſee only Doctor <hi>VValker</hi> ſtaid all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſilver, I ſtayed the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſilver.</p>
               <p>At laſt when <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> ſaw his Error, in taking on himſelf the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in his ſingle perſon, and in looking after the ſilver mines in <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and ſeizing upon the ſilver, as I had ſet him to do, he curſed me often times bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly; Mr. <hi>Beck</hi> of <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> being <hi>Oliver Cromwels</hi> Sollicitor, and Maſter <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> the Maſter of his Requeſt: I uſed them to ſollicit my buſineſs to <hi>Cromwel,</hi> for to get ſatisfaction for my eſtate unjuſtly taken away, but they both told me, he would never do nothing for me, for he hated my name and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance; and that whenſoever they moved him of my name concerning any buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he would be in a rage; Mr. <hi>Beck,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> ſeveral times have asked me whether I could imagine the reaſon? I told them No, I wondred at it.</p>
               <p>But indeed I know the reaſon, he did ſee I had ſet him on thoſe things which he was not able to maſter, and though I put on it the face of innocency I knew from the firſt hour that <hi>Cromwell</hi> took the 278250 <hi>l.</hi> into his cuſtody, that he would deſtroy the Parliament, and divide and ſubdivide among themſelves, till all ended in confuſion: I thought it my duty to give your Majeſtie, this true Accompt and can prove it as aforeſaid, and ſeveral other ſervices, your Petitioner hath done for your Majeſtie, where in every on he ventured his life for your Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and never had farthing either of the Parliament or <hi>Cromwell,</hi> but expended his own money for ſeveral years, to the value of fifteen hundred pounds. And twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand pounds taken from me by the Parliament as aforeſaid. There are many of the then Honourable Priſoners in the Tower can tell your Majeſtie, how active <hi>I</hi> was always in your Majeſties Fathers ſervice in the Tower: <hi>I</hi> humbly refer my ſelf to this following Certificate for the loſs of my Eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="certificate">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:102645:22"/>
               <p>THeſe are to Certifie, whom it may concern; That I <hi>William Du-Gard</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Clerk, have known <hi>Thomas Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Goldſmith many years; and have been privy to his Applications to the Parliament, for reſtoring him to his eſtate, taken from him by the Parliament in 1643. for his bringing up a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Peace to the City of <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>Oxford,</hi> from his late Majeſtie CHARLES the <hi>I.</hi> of bleſſed Memory; And I have ſeen Mr. <hi>Violets</hi> Original Petitions, Accounts, and Demands of the Long Parliament, for ſatisfaction for his Eſtate, in Lands, Houſes, Offices, Bonds, Debts, Goods, to the value of above eleven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds; ſo much hath been confeſſed to me by ſeveral of the Committee of Parliament, that Examined the ſaid <hi>Tho. Violets</hi> ſufferings, that they found it fully proved Mr. <hi>Violets</hi> Loſſes to be above the ſumme of eleven thouſand pounds, beſides his Impriſonment and forbearance. And I have heard ſeveral Parliament men confeſſe, that Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> was unjuſtly oppreſsed, contrary to Gods Law and mans, for being ſequeſtred for bringing up the Kings Letter for Peace; and ſeveral Members of Parliament, upon my Solicitation promiſed him from time to time ſatisfaction, but abuſed him by delays, making him for many years loſe both time, and expend much money in waiting on them to my knowledge; but never received farthing from them.</p>
               <p>I do further teſtifie, upon the Peruſall of Mr. <hi>Violets</hi> Papers, and the Confeſſion of ſeveral of his Neighbours, who knew him before the Year 1643. that I do eſteem his Loſſes to be far above eleven thouſand pounds ſince 1643. beſides his Impriſonment, and loſſe of his Calling, to his damage at this time above twenty thouſand pounds. In witneſſe whereof I have here to ſubſcribed my Hand.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>WILL. DU-GARD.</signed>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:102645:23"/>
                        <head>The ſame is in Effect certified by ſeveral other Gentlemen, whoſe Names are ſubſcribed, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <item>ALEXANDER HOLT <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>Goldſmith.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>WILLIAM BOURNE <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>Brewer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>PAUL SMITH <hi>of</hi> London <hi>Gentlemen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>ROBERT EMERY <hi>of</hi> London <hi>Gentlemen.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <head>Witneſſes.</head>
                        <item>Joſiah Smith.</item>
                        <item>Paul Edwards.</item>
                        <item>John Wegewood.</item>
                        <item>Henry Goldſton.</item>
                        <item>VVilliam Barnes</item>
                        <item>Knight ey Freeman.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A true Coppy of Doctor <hi>Walkers</hi> report concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Silver Ships the 14th of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1654. To OLIVER CROMWELS Councel.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your Honours,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IN the buſineſs concerning the Ships and Silver goods in the three Ships in the <hi>Samſon, Salvador,</hi> and S. <hi>George</hi> upon attending your Lordſhips, with Mr. <hi>Violet,</hi> ſeverall particular were propoſed, and I was directed by your Honours ſummarily, to ſtate them, and to give my humble opinion upon every of them.</p>
               <p>The particulars were,</p>
               <p>1. Concerning the Silver in theſe three Ships, which was the bulk of the whole matter upon which I argued, when I procured the <hi>Onus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandi</hi> to be caſt on the other ſide.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> devided it thus, that there was one <hi>Boſchard</hi> a Hamburger, and one <hi>Stephen de Balderos,</hi> and one <hi>Lewis Fardinandes Hagelo,</hi> and one <hi>Loſa Berona;</hi> and one <hi>Mexico Herera,</hi> and one <hi>Michaell Severino Lozenſo de Eucle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and one <hi>Thomas Sauches, de Uriſe Anthonio de Puntho Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> and one <hi>Dony Martin</hi> Native of <hi>Galloway</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that laid particular claims every of them, to ſome parcels of the Silver laden for their accompts all whom (as Mr. <hi>Violet Stated it</hi>) came along in the ſaid Ships and have attended their claims here ever ſince upon the place, in making their proofs and ſollicitings; for bringing it on to a hearing for their particulars and are as Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> ſtates it, by their long attendance and ſpending in diet and otherwiſe reduced to ſuch extremity as they for want are ready to ſtarve.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:102645:23"/>
               <p>For theſe Mr. <hi>Violet,</hi> hath propoſed that his Highneſs and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips would direct that their claims would come on to a preſent hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that ſo what was found to be juſtly and really theirs might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged them: not onely for their preſent relief, but for the vindicating (as Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> terms it) the juſtice of the Nation, and preventing any Imbargoes abroad for want of juſtice here.</p>
               <p>Now for this my Lords being as I conceive, rather the prudential part then the legal, I muſt not take upon me to give any opinion in it, but ſubmit it wholly to your Lordſhips to conſider the prudence of it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will hold it fit that theſe particulars ſhall come on before the reſt of the claims; for the other Silver in the ſaid Ships and ſo to handle by pieces, or whether to have all the Silver directed by tryall and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether.</p>
               <p>For the reſt being the great bulks of the Silver, Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> propoſed that pleas ſhould be put in, to be a ground for Commiſſioners to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to go into <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> to examine witneſſes there; againſt the ſeveral claimers, and their claims ſuppoſing that in reſpect the Laws of <hi>Spain</hi> prohibit the carrying out of Silver under great penalties, the claymors would not dare to own it in <hi>Spain,</hi> if Commiſſioners for his Highneſs, ſhould be ſent over thither and that much diſcoveries would there be made, and witneſſes be found in <hi>Spain</hi> if active perſons be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and ſent over thither.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> propoſed that there would be this farther uſe made of it, by procraſtinating the buſineſſes, and gaining of ſo long time as for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to go into <hi>Spain,</hi> and be executed there and returned.</p>
               <p>As to the laſt of theſe it is evident, that it muſt of neceſſity gain time, and delay the hearing.</p>
               <p>But whether upon the main matter, it will produce any thing or countervaile the charge, which muſt needs iſſue out of purſe and cannot but be vaſt in exceuting ſo many Commiſſions by the Magiſtrates of <hi>Spain,</hi> and imploying ſuch as muſt neceſſarily, be ſent over to look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, I have often told Mr. <hi>Violet,</hi> that I much doubt and muſt ſubmit it to your Lordſhips, not daring of my ſelf to venture upon it; without a ſpecial warrant, for ſeveral reaſons.</p>
               <p>1. For that we yet know of never a particular witneſs by name to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine when we came thither.</p>
               <p>2. And for that it will be uncertain whether after ſo great acharg ſpent to make inquiry there, any poſitive witneſſes would be there or not.</p>
               <p>3. If any there ſhall be found it will be uncertain whether upon the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102645:24"/> clay mors croſs interogatories they may not ſay more againſt us, then upon ours for us, being there in a Countrey where the claymors will in all likelihood finde more means, friends and opportunities, then thoſe that ſhall be ſent over from hence againſt them.</p>
               <p>4. For that the claymors have already upon their own Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, owned their claims in <hi>Spain,</hi> and examined witneſſes by the Magiſtrates publickly there upon; and therfore no doubt, but they may again publickly avow them at ours, if any new Commiſſions go from hence for his Highneſs: as well as they did upon their own claims when Commiſſions iſſued to <hi>Spain,</hi> for them which they have procured to be there ſpeeded and returned back again hither into Court.</p>
               <p>And therefore what your Lordſhips propoſed to me as firſt in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that is, to endeavour that publication for the claimors might ſo paſs, that liberty might be given to ſee their proofs, and yet if occaſion were to plead and examine witneſſes notwithſtanding, which Albeit, the rule be that contrary matter may not be examined upon after pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication and ſight of the witneſſes; yet in thoſe caſes of the Silver in the ſaid three Ships, I have ſince I waited upon your Lordſhips, upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates with the adverſe Proctors and Councels publickly in Court pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured ſuch a <hi>Salvo</hi> by their conſents to be entred and publication is ſo paſt that now the deſpoſitions and proofs for the claimors may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, and yet liberty to plead and examine for his Highneſs (if there be occaſion) notwithſtanding; but there being ſo many Commiſſions returned for the claimors, and the depoſitions ſo extream long, It will ask a good time to puruſe and conſider them.</p>
               <p>As to the reſt of the goods in thoſe Ships, not being Silver, many of them, being much decayed and periſhed by ſo long lying, and ſome of them having been heard already and for what remaines, I ſee no reaſon at all to put off the hearing of them any longer; for that the main charge ſuſpicions and grounds were againſt the Silver: and had not (as I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive) any ſuch reflex upon the Tobaccoes, Hides, and other goods; &amp; beſides ſuch ſpecial proviſions may be made (as hath alſo been already done in what hath been heard) that they may have no manner of conſequence at all, as to any of the Silver.</p>
               <p>And as to the Ships themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Sampſon, Salvador,</hi> and St. <hi>George,</hi> for as much as the publick Agent for <hi>Hamborough</hi> hath often preſſed it, that they might be permitted to come to hearing, &amp; for that by this long lying, one of the ſaid Ships hath been already ſunk in the River; and that if the ſaid Ships ſhould be continued much longer
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102645:24"/> without repairing and imployment, it is publickly (and hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) affirmed in Court, that they will decay, periſh and come to nothing.<note place="margin">Truly Doctor <hi>Walker,</hi> if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you or <hi>O. Cromwel</hi> had known upon what grounds or reaſons I ſtaid this ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, you (as <hi>O. Cromwels</hi> Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Judge Advocate) would have paid me as you did the <hi>Kentiſh</hi> men for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring for the King. I was forewarned of truſting of you by ſeveral of the Kings friends, who remembred how you ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Biſhop <hi>Williams</hi> in the Star-chamber. Indeed you told me <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> nor the Parliament would never give mee any thing, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they would be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by me &amp; give me no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, after they had rok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me of all my eſtate they could finger, I was reſolved to give them that advice to be revenged of them, that if they took it, it ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both the Parliament and <hi>Cromwel.</hi> God it was that incouraged me and blinded them, that they ſhould ever truſt a mans advice that they had ruined. They ſhould have remembred that advice, <hi>Truſt not a pretended reconciled adverſary;</hi> eſpecially keeping him from his eſtate, as they did me to this day to my dammage Twenty thouſand pounds. Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> junior having a better noſe than the reſt, ever ſaid I was not to be truſted, telling <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> I had ſeveral times made my application to him, but he would have nothing to do with me: and when I ſtayed the Silver, <hi>Vane</hi> moved to ſend me to the Tower; for (ſaid he at the Council) this Villain will ſet us againſt al the world at once, to bring in the King of Scots; I wonder the Council claps him not up. Thereupon it was put to the queſtion: whereof 10 of them were for laying me in priſon, and 12 for giving me thanks; all thoſe that were of the then Council of State knows this to be true, That I made a fraction between <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and <hi>Vane. Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> with the reſt of their party about the ſtaying the Silver, but <hi>Vane, Strick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Nevil</hi> were for letting of it go. This Silver which I ſtayed was the only cauſe of blowing up the Long Parliament, which I knew at that time an Army of 40000 men could not have done.</note> I do humbly conceive ſubmitting it nevertheleſs to your Lordſhips that for the avoiding of further periſhing of the ſaid Snips, and other lading (not being Silver) and for avoiding claimour and ſcandal in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of juſtice, The ſaid Ships, and remainder of the lading (except the Silver) may if your Lordſhips pleaſe, be permitted to come to a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and judgement.</p>
               <p>As for Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> himſelf, I can onely ſay that by ſeverall Orders of the former Councell of State; he was directed to ſollicite and look after this buſineſſe of the Silver Ships, and that he hath often attended and ſpoken in Court, and many times repaired to me, and conſulted about it; and that it hath appeared to me (and may alſo to your Lordſhips by peruſing what he hath printed) he hath ſpent much time about it, and I verily believe hath drawn much envy upon himſelf, and run ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and danger and ſpent his own monies in going up and down to make his enquiries. But I cannot determine what the produce or effect thereof will be, or amount unto untill ſome particular and poſitive proofs be brought in to prove the Silver, or at leaſt ſome part thereof really and truely to belong to ſome <hi>Hollanders,</hi> ſpecifying their names, and the parcells, and diſcovering the fraud, in colouring it in other feigned names.</p>
               <p>For as I have humbly declared unto your Lordſhips, for as much as the <hi>Onus probandi</hi> is by Law caſt upon the claimors. The reſult is, that for ſo much as the claimors ſhall not poſitively and certainly make ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and particular proofs of: there the judgement will be for confil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in default of their proof, in reſpect of the <hi>Onus Probandi</hi> ſo caſt.</p>
               <p>But for ſo much as the claimors ſhall make, &amp; have made poſitive par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular &amp; concludent proofs, of their real property. There I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive unleſs more proofs be brought in, then yet are, or that Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> can bring in certain and particular proofs, to encounter the other that in references and arguments will be of no more force, then the caſting of the <hi>Onus probandi</hi> alone will do of it ſelf, ſo that I dare not take upon me to give any opinion, But muſt leave the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> and his ſervice to your Lordſhips.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>All which I humbly Submit Walter Walker.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>April 14. 1654</date>.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="warrant">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:102645:25"/>
               <p>By Command from King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed Memory, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by Warrant under his Royal Hand and Seal, I cauſed theſe men following to be fined in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> for tranſporting Gold and Silver, and culling and melting down the heavie Coine of the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="2">The 25th. of Ian. 12. Car.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">The 17th. of Febr. 12 Car.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Charles Frank</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4000 l.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Peter Hern</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2000 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Robert Ellis</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4000 l.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>John Tere</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2000 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iſaac Romeer</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3000 l.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Timothie Eman</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2000 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Jacob Delew</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1000 l.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iſaac Brames</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1000 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Roger Fletcher</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1000 l.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Henry Futter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>500 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Richard Cockram</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1000 l.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Henry Sweeting</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>500 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>John Parrat</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1000 l.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>John Perrin</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>100 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="4">
                           <hi>The Total of the ſaid Fines amount to the ſumme of</hi> 23100 l.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>This Sentence awed the Tranſporters of Gold, till theſe Troubles, they durſt not tranſport Gold or Silver, for fear I ſhould meet with them.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>John Wollaſton</hi> Knight, and <hi>William Gibs</hi> Eſquire, both Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> being informed againſt in this Information, by the then Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-General, procured a Pardon from your Majeſties Royal Father, and ſo were diſcharged. Theſe two villains betrayed your Royal Father. 1643. As aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And Mr. <hi>Peter Fountain,</hi> who was informed againſt for Tranſporting of Gold by me, procured his Pardon upon paiment of 1100 l. to the Lord of St. <hi>Albanes,</hi> then Maſter <hi>Jermyn.</hi> And all theſe I did bring to a Trial, at my own charge.</p>
               <p>That beſides the fourteen offenders ſentenced in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, as aforeſaid, there are many other Merchants, Gold-ſmiths, and others, that have tranſported Gold and Silver out of the Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="legal_document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Die Mercurii 1 Sept. 1647.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>ORdered by the Commons in Parliament Aſſembled, That it be referred to the Committee of the Navie to conſider of, and take ſome effectual courſe to prevent the Tranſportation of Bullion out of the Kingdom: and ſpeedily to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port what they have done herein, to the Houſe.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H. Elſing. <hi>Cler. Parl,</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102645:25"/>
               <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſty, to peruſe your Royal Fathers letter, which I have printed in this book, folio 14, wherein his late Majeſty of glorious memory, commands me that I ſhould not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the tranſpotters of Gold and Silver to the Parliament, without his Majeſties eſpecial licence. His Majeſty knew the fines and compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the offenders would bring the Parliament in great ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which they would then imploy againſt him, being then upon the point to call the <hi>Scotch</hi> then to invade the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> deſtroy his Majeſty, and the Royal party.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time I had in the Parliament my Patent under examinati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on in the Houſe of Commons, for an Office I have for two lives, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Royal Fathers great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> for the eſſaying and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Gold and Silver Wire, and Silver, and Gold Thrid, and to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the ſame to the Wearers, that it be good Silver, and a due proportion of Silver to Silk. This Patent was commanded by Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Harlow,</hi> being Chair man to a Committee, to be brought into the Houſe and referred to a Committee, who after ſeveral daies hearing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred all parties to the Law, concerning the regulation of Gold and Silver wier.</p>
               <p>And I juſtified my Patent to be for the good of the Kingdom in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and that it ſaved fifty thouſand pounds a year by my ſaid office, and by my regulation and tying the workmen to work good Silver, and a due proportion of Silver to Silk; and this I humbly ſay at this day to be true, as I will prove it at the Council for Trade.</p>
               <p>There was a Committee appointed, and <hi>Pim, Hamden, Whittaker, Corbet, &amp;c.</hi> to article with me for to diſcover the tranſporters of Gold and Silver, and if I would do that, and raiſe the Parliament monies by the fines of the offenders, then I was by their procurement that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Parliament ſhould report the legalty and juſtice of my afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Patent and Office; and it ſhould have been confirmed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but firſt I was to raiſe the Parliament fourty thouſand pounds by the fines of the tranſporters of Gold.</p>
               <p>This agreement was made between the Committee of Parliament and me, in the Court of Wards, about the 10th. of November 1643. and I prepared to make my diſcovery accordingly. But then, may it pleaſe your Majeſtie, comes your Majeſties Fathers Letter, of bleſſed memorie, and commands me not to do this ſervice for the Parliament at my peril, as <hi>I</hi> have it to ſhew under his Majeſties hand and Seal. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon preſently <hi>I</hi> obeyed his Sacred Letter, and choſe Poverty and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102645:26"/> before Riches, and to be a Rebel for my Loyalty <hi>I</hi> have been moſt Barbarouſly uſed.</p>
               <p>I told the Committee, that upon enquiry after the buſineſs, I found the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants, and ſtrangers, that had tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Gold and ſilver out of the Nation; were removed from <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> and I could not for the preſent do them that ſervice I had promiſed them.</p>
               <p>Whereupon <hi>Whittaker</hi> and <hi>Corbet</hi> took that but for a flam, and ſaid, I was your Majeſties Royal Fathers Spie, a Cavalier, and a Malignant, and moved the Houſe againſt me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they ſent me to the Kings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bench; and there I remained a Priſoner, till I made an exchange for Mr. <hi>Heſlerig,</hi> then Priſoner at <hi>Beaver</hi> Caſtle 1643. in <hi>December.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>January</hi> after his late Majeſtie had exchanged me, preſently he commands me to bring up the Letter aforeſaid, from his late Majeſty to the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> which I did, and the barbarous abuſes which I received from Citie and Parliament, for bringing the ſame up, I have humbly declared.</p>
               <p>My humble requeſt unto your Maieſty is, that you would be pleaſed to obſerve, all my ſuffering is only for my loyalty to your Maieſties Royal Father, would I have obeyed the Parliament, and diſcovered the Tranſporters of Gold at that time, 1643. I had inioyed all my eſtate, and been ſetled in the Office which I have for two Lives for the regulating Gold and Silver Thred and Wyer.</p>
               <p>And all this damage I ſuffered for obeying your Maieſties Royal Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to my damage at this day above twenty thouſand pounds: My moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition to your Majeſty is, That ſeeing I was oppreſſed and traduced by the tyranny of Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> junior, Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig,</hi> and Mr. St. <hi>John,</hi> they being the principal Actors that ruined me, that I may have by your Majeſties goodneſs, bounty, and mercy, allotted out of Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrigs,</hi> and Sir <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Vanes</hi> eſtates ſuch ſatisfaction and reparation as your Maieſty in your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al wiſdom ſhall think fit and juſt for my ſupport, after ſo ſad an oppreſſion for my loyalty to your Royal Father, the petition to the Parliament, and my charge againſt <hi>Vane, St. John, Haſlerig,</hi> was put into the Parliament before your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties gracious Letter from <hi>Breda,</hi> the Lords in Parliament ordered me to reſpite my Petition to them, until your Maieſties happy arrival into <hi>England,</hi> and ever ſince I watched my opportunity to ſhew what I have done and ſuffered for your Royal Father, and what I can and will do for Your Majeſties Royal ſervice, if you pleaſe to command me, I am at your ſervice, as far as my life and eſtate will go.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:102645:26"/>
               <p>MAY it pleaſe your Majeſty, in the year 1636. your Majeſties Royal Father gave Alderman <hi>Wollaſton,</hi> and Alderman <hi>Gibbs</hi> his Gratious pardon, Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay,</hi> and the Company of Goldſmiths, charged Alderman <hi>VVol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſton</hi> for buying the Kings ſtollen Plate, and Alderman <hi>Gibbs,</hi> for refining and melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Silver contrary to the Lawes, as will appear in the Records of the Councel-Table, about <hi>March</hi> 1635. Had not his Royal Majeſty of bleſſed memory pardoned the then Lord Major <hi>Wollaſton,</hi> the Law had hanged him before ever he had come to have been Lord Major of <hi>London;</hi> and then he ſhould have prevented this <hi>VVollaſton</hi> from being ſuch a Traitor to his Majeſty, the Proverb ſaith, <hi>Save a Thief from the gallows and he will hang thee:</hi> This <hi>VVolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> proved a bloody enemy to the King to his dying day, and <hi>Gibbs</hi> as bad as he, but is yet living.</p>
               <p>For as ſoon as ever I delivered his Majeſties Meſſage unto my Lord Major, he ſent for his fellow Traitor Alderman <hi>Gibbs,</hi> and they preſently concluded to make Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> junior, Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> Mr Sollici or <hi>St. John,</hi> and <hi>Francis Allen,</hi> acquainted with the Kings Letter, and ordered preſently to apprehend me, Sir <hi>Baſil Brook,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rily</hi> to ſeize upon our Eſtates and ſequeſter us: And ſo preſently I was that night apprehended, and for four years ſo uſed, that never any man that brought up a Letter from any King of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> for a Peace, was ſo barbarouſly and cruelly uſed, that Evening the aforeſaid perſons and ſome others examined me they carried me to Goldſmiths Hall, they ſent for Sir <hi>Baſil Brock,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rily,</hi> and <hi>St. John</hi> the Kings Sollicitor cauſed all our Pockets to be ſearched, and found their Letters in Sir <hi>Baſil Brocks</hi> and <hi>Rilies,</hi> but none in mine, and as Sir <hi>Baſil Brook</hi> preſented him with the Kings Letter, which I brought up from <hi>Oxford; St. John</hi> asked Sir <hi>Baſil Brook</hi> for another Letter, which the Kings Majeſty had ſent up, the day before I went to <hi>Oxford</hi> to preſſe <hi>Rily</hi> and his party, to act their buſineſs as ſoon as they could, with a Letter from my Lord <hi>George Digby,</hi> which the Officers found about Sir <hi>Baſil Brook.</hi> Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this buſineſs when they had theſe Letters, St. <hi>Johns, Vane, Haſelrig,</hi> Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> Lord Major <hi>Wollaſton,</hi> and Alderman <hi>Gibbs,</hi> and ſeveral others, made themſelves very merry with them. There was Mr. <hi>Jackson</hi> the Eſſay-Maſter of Goldſmiths Hall, a very honeſt man, and one that ſaved my life at that time, in diſcovering to me what was confeſſed by <hi>Rily,</hi> that he had not diſcovered any thing, and that the aforeſaid Committee were reſolved to face me down <hi>Rilie</hi> had confeſſed all, and ſo would have me to diſcover, and I ſhould have mercie.</p>
               <p>They found in Mr. <hi>Rilies</hi> pockets <hi>Reads</hi> two Letters aforeſaid, and threatned him to have him racked, if he would not diſcover the bottom of the buſineſſe, and who they were in the Citie, that plotted to oppoſe the <hi>Scots</hi> coming in.</p>
               <p>But there was an Oath of Secrecy amongſt them all, and <hi>Rilie</hi> knew them all, but I was not privy to the number that was but only to act with Sir <hi>Baſil Brook, Read,</hi> and at <hi>Oxford</hi> with his Majeſtie, the Queens Majeſtie, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> and to bring the Kings Letter from <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had <hi>Rily</hi> but confeſſed thoſe Gentlemen in <hi>London</hi> that wete privie with him
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102645:27"/> in this buſineſs he had made many ſcore of men in the City of <hi>London,</hi> loſe their Lives and Eſtates.</p>
               <p>And had the Lord Major <hi>VVollaſton</hi> concealed the buſineſs twenty four hours, it had been out of his power to have ſtopped this deſign for peace: His late Majeſty of bleſſed memory told me at <hi>Oxford,</hi> That <hi>Rily</hi> had ſent him down by one that came purpoſely to <hi>Read</hi> from <hi>London,</hi> a Liſt of above two hundred of the principal men that had ingaged in this buſineſs, every man upon an Oath of ſecreſie: The late King commanded me to tell Mr. <hi>Rilie</hi> Scoutmaſter-gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the City, that he ſhould follow his former Directions, which was to be careful whom he imparted this buſineſs to, and to treat with them ſeverally, and not together, for all their ſecurity depended thereon, that it did concern all our Lives and Eſtates to be circumſpect: We had former Preſidents to make us wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Tomkins</hi> and <hi>Challenor</hi> and others, and though he was careful of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, yet of thoſe that were moſt forward to ſerve him, he was moſt tender that they ſhould venture themſelves, telling me he did know more of this deſign then I did, by Gods bleſſing it will take ſaith his Majeſtie, I have laid it ſo with Mr <hi>Rily,</hi> that I am aſſured of a happy ſucceſs, go thy way, I will make thee a man, and tell my Lord Major, and Mr. <hi>Rilie,</hi> I will make them famous for ever. <hi>Rily</hi> was by all parties truſted to carry on this deſign, and had not the ſins of the Nation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented us of ſuch a mercy (for it was not Gods time) for our deliverance, there was never in all theſe troubles a deſign for putting an end to the War without bloodſhed, ſo laid and contrived as Sir <hi>Baſil Brook,</hi> Col. <hi>Read,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rily,</hi> had laid every man his part ſeverally; and ſo ſecretly, that though the principal men in the City were ingaged in the buſineſs to make the City of <hi>London</hi> to declare for the King, and to oppoſe the <hi>Scots</hi> invading of <hi>England,</hi> and the Cities Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they intended to publiſh; I brought it to his Majeſty my ſelf 1643. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived my Orders and Directions thereupon my ſelf from his Majeſty, and the Queens moſt excellent Majeſty, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Georgs Digby</hi> his Majeſties Secretary and Coll. <hi>Read,</hi> were only privie to this buſineſſe; to my knowledge, at the Court, and no other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <head>Two Letters of Col. <hi>Read's,</hi> ſent to Mr. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus Rily,</hi> Scout-maſter of the City of <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>Oxford,</hi> to incourage the Common-Councel of the City of <hi>London,</hi> to Petition his late Majeſty for Peace; and to conſider the ſad Effects that would follow, upon the <hi>Scots</hi> invading-<hi>England.</hi> Jan. 1643.</head>
               <div type="letter">
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Wrote to you formerly, but never had any Anſwer, I aſſure you faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully I have not been wanting to do what you deſired (as you may perceiv by the effects) &amp; if you have not your deſire, blame your ſelf,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102645:27"/> and give me leave to tell you, that if you neglect the opportunity now of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to you, it may be you ſhall never have the like again; for I have made thoſe whom you have given juſt occaſion to be your worſt friends, to be your beſt, and the only inſtruments to procure what here is ſent you, and be you confident ſhee ſhall ſtill be ſo, provided you do your part;<note place="margin">The Queens moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty, in my hearing, (I being ſent down to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> by order of <hi>Rilie</hi> and ſome others, to bring up his Majeſties Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1643.) did moſt earneſtly intercede for the City of <hi>London.</hi> The King there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon replied, that he had there the beſt and worſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of any King in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom;</hi> and hereupon the Queen replied, <hi>Violet</hi> it ſhall be my care to ſee the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that come from the City with a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the King ſhall be well accomodated, and have a moſt Gratious Anſwer to all their juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God bleſſe them, &amp; God increaſe their number, and thereupon the Queens Majeſty wept, and the King drew his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief out of his pocket, and the tears ſtood in the Kings eyes, which made both <hi>Read</hi> and I fall a weeping, and thereupon the Queen commanded Col. <hi>Read</hi> to lift up the Hangings, to ſee no body ſtood behinde the Hangings to hear what ſhee ſaid, which <hi>Read</hi> did, and when the Queen ſee no body behinde the Hangings; Ah <hi>Violet</hi> ſaid ſhe the King and I am in a moſt ſad condition, we have Traytors about us, that watch all our Words and Actions, we ſpeak nothing, nor do nothing, but it is ſeat up to the Parliament, and they interpret it in the worſt Sence: The Queens Majeſty at that time was very ill, and lookt very carefully, and was nothing but Skin and Bones. God be thanked for the bleſſed change that is here at this day, the Kings Majeſty her Son, in the Throne of his Royal Father, and King of the hearts of his People; theſe two Papers was found in <hi>Rilies</hi> pockets, and was printed by Order of Parliament, and Col. <hi>Read</hi> charged to be a Jeſuite, I am ſure of it theſe Papers makes him a true Prophet, I ſaved <hi>Reads</hi> life in getting him exchanged of the General <hi>Eſſex</hi> by a wrong name.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I beſeech you, what a gap is opened by bringing in of the <hi>Scots,</hi> for the deſtruction of this Kingdom, if there be not a Peace (which I pray God Almightie to ſend ſpeedily) you muſt expect Armies of Strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from ſeveral Places, who are now preparing, who certainly at their coming in will over-run the whole Kingdom, and when it is paſt remedy, you will ſee your own Errors, and therefore to prevent more miſery then I am able to expreſſe to this deplorable Kingdom, and the effuſion of the bloud of thouſands of men, women, and children, which muſt inevitably be this Summer; apply your ſelves in an humble and ſubmiſſive way to his Majeſtie, whom I know you will finde ready with Arms out-ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to receive you to favor and mercy, and grant you favors, even beyond your expectation. Defer no time (for God's ſake) and what you will do, do it ſpeedily; I ſay again, do it ſpeedily, for reaſons, I may not write.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Oxford <date>Dec. 10. 1560</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>Col. <hi>Read's</hi> Paper to Mr. <hi>Rilie,</hi> Scoutmaſter of the City of LONDON.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Aſſure you that I have not been wanting to further your good deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and if it be not your own faults, I make no doubt but things will have an happy iſſue; for I finde thoſe that are moſt concerned in it, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102645:28"/> enough. Reflect now upon the miſerie of the times, and upon the groans and ſufferings of thoſe you ſee not, which yet have been nothing to what they will be, if not ſpeedily prevented by a Peace; which to obtain I beſeech you, let it not only be your own care, but the care of all thoſe you love, or have power with, otherwiſe be confident of a generall ruine, which certainly will be inevitable both to your ſelves and poſteritie; and therefore take it into your ſerious conſideration, and let no cauſleſs jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies hinder you to apply your ſelves in an humble and ſubmiſſive man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to his Majestie, who I am ſure will yet look upon you with a gracious eie; loſe no time, for the longer you delay, it may prove the more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, no doubt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>This laſt Letter I <hi>Tho. Violet</hi> delivered from <hi>Read</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Rilie</hi> in <hi>London Decemb. 20. 1640.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Coll. <hi>Read</hi> I got exchanged by a wrong name, for a private Souldier, at the intreatie of Sir <hi>Baſil Brook,</hi> who told me I ſhould do a very good ſervice for his Majeſtie, and the Queens Majeſtie, to get <hi>Read</hi> to be diſcharged, but that muſt be done by a wrong name, or elſe ſaid Sir <hi>Baſil Brook</hi> the Parliament would never admit of his exchang; <hi>I</hi> did effect it, and ſent this Coll. <hi>Read</hi> to the King at <hi>Oxford,</hi> upon condition he would returne to Mr. <hi>Rilie</hi> the Scout-maſter of <hi>London,</hi> how he found his Majeſtie inclined to receive a Petition from the City of <hi>London</hi> for peace, that they would declare themſelves for a peace, and Petition his Majeſtie for a ceſſation of Arms; and an accommodation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the late King of Glorious memory. And <hi>I Tho. Violet</hi> was ſent down to <hi>Oxford Decemb. 29 1643</hi> to bring up his Majeſties Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Letter, the Copie of the Citie of <hi>London<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> deſire, being ſent to his late Majeſtie, wherein they deſired upon the Copie I brought to Oxford,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102645:28"/> to have his Majeſtie directed his Letter to the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> but his late Majestie would not own the <hi>Militia,</hi> to treat with them as the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Citie, becauſe his Majeſtie told me at <hi>Oxford</hi> they were not impowred by his Commiſſion, and he would not own them: I told his late Majeſtie, and the Lord <hi>Digbie,</hi> it was contrary to my instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which I received from Mr. <hi>Rilie,</hi> to alter the ſuperſcription of His Majeſties Letter, but ſeeing His Majeſtie would not but direct his Letter, <hi>To our Lord Mayor, and Aldermen of our City of</hi> London, <hi>and all other our well affected Subjects of that our Citie.</hi> I would venture my life to bring up this Letter to <hi>London,</hi> and going according to my inſtructions I received from his Maieſtie, to acquaint <hi>Wolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> then Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> and Alderman <hi>Gibbs,</hi> they cauſed me ſome few houres after I was gon from them, to be apprehended upon a Charge of High Treaſon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>
                  <hi>MAy it pleaſe your Majeſty</hi> to peruſe this enſuing Narrative, viz. in <hi>Sept.</hi> 1657. I being ſick ſent to <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> to write to the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Protector <hi>Cromwell,</hi> that if he would not pay me the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thouſand pounds he promiſed me, to pay me ſome conſiderable ſum for my ſupport. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> at that time wrote to <hi>Cromwell</hi> very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to pay me a conſiderable ſum in part, uſing this as his argument, and telling Mr <hi>Beck (Cromwels</hi> Solicitour) Mr <hi>Tho. Hewet,</hi> and Mr <hi>Yates</hi> my Chirurgeon (who were all three by when <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> wrote to the pretended Protector about me) <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> ſaid, Remember my ſervice to my Lord Protector, and deſire him in my name to pay <hi>Violet</hi> a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of his money for his ſupport, according to his quality; my Lord Protector knowes not <hi>Violet</hi> ſo well as I do: If the man ſhould go to <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> he would do us more miſchief than a hundred thouſand pounds would do us good: there are ſome Kings would give an hundred thouſand pounds for to have ſuch an Engine for their turn, and they knew him as well as I do. This meſſage was ſent to <hi>Cromwel</hi> from <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> by Mr <hi>Beck</hi> the Protectors Solicitour; Mr <hi>Hewet,</hi> Mr <hi>Yates,</hi> and theſe Gentlemen are all in <hi>London</hi> to juſtifie this to be true.</p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Beck</hi> upon this meſſage moved Mr <hi>Francis Bacon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the maſter of the Requeſt, to move <hi>Cromwel</hi> the Protector effectually about me, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102645:29"/> he would alſo move him; which they did, and they both told mee when my name was but mentioned for my money I petitioned for, <hi>Cromwel</hi> was ſo incenſed againſt me, that he beſtowed all the bad words in the world, and ſaid, that he took me to be a dangerous perſon, and an Arrant Villain againſt him; and, in a word (ſaith Mr <hi>Bacon</hi> and Mr <hi>Beck</hi>) he takes thee to be an Arrant Knave. They often asked me if I could i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine the reaſon that the Protector, and ſome of his Council, was ſo bitter againſt me, that they never heard man have a worſe character than <hi>Cromwel</hi> did give me, and ſome of his Council that were intimate with him, as <hi>Thurloe,</hi> &amp;c. I replyed, I received good for evil, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors payment to me is not currant to revile me for venturing my life in his ſervice, and laying out of my purſe 1500l. to get him 278250l. ſo much money <hi>Baxter</hi> paid him clear for the ſilver I ſtaid him in the ſhips <hi>Sampſon, Salvador</hi> and St <hi>George,</hi> as will appear by an Ordinance of Parliament for <hi>Baxters</hi> diſcharge for the payment of that money. I knew <hi>Cromwels</hi> reaſon, but would not tell it to them. For I found (when it was too late) he knew he had undone himſelf, by ſeizing on this Silver and breaking up the Parliament; and that I was the fatal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument that adviſed him to take the Silver into his own cuſtody, either under the Ban quetting houſe to lodg it, or in the Tower. He did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I did it innocently and for his good; for had he believed I had done (as truly I did) malitiouſly to deſtroy him, he would have cauſed me to have been torn in pieces.</p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Strickland</hi> asked one Capt. <hi>Swan,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Kent,</hi> an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate friend of mine, what he thought I was, and whether I was not a Cavaleer; <hi>Strickland</hi> telling Captain <hi>Swan,</hi> Many of us of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State take <hi>Violet</hi> to be a ſly and dangerous fellow, he is alwayes preſenting Propoſitions unto us which may bear double interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; he pretends for the Councils profit, but I am ſure it is for their danger; he hath ſtaid Three hundred thouſand pounds in Silver, and hath ſet us together by the ears amongſt our ſelves, and with <hi>Holland: Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> makes uſe of him, promiſing him from day to day to give him his Eſtate, but they but abuſe him, they will never give him a farthing. I heard <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> ſay, I could wiſh <hi>Violet</hi> had his Eſtate or the value, but there is no truſting him therein. If he ſhould run to the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> he would do us more miſchief than a hundred thouſand pounds. Keep him poor, and that will keep him honeſt to us: for if he had his Eſtate, he would be with the King of <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="examples_of_coinage_regulation">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:102645:29"/>
               <p>The King of <hi>France</hi> hath a ſtanding Councel for to Regulate his Mints, and to hinder the Tranſporting of Gold or Silver. VVere the like Orders ſetled in <hi>England,</hi> it would be for your Majeſties ſervice, and keep your Majeſties Mint on work.</p>
               <div type="ordinance">
                  <head>IN an Ordinance and Declaration of the King of <hi>France,</hi> printed at <hi>Paris,</hi> 30. Oct 1640. Fol. 8, 9.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>We expreſly forbid, that all Materials of Gold or Silver, either coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or uncoined, ſhall not be bought and ſold at higher Rates, then is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet down in this Declaration, which doth declare the true value that muſt be paied for the Mark of Silver.</p>
                     <p>We expreſly forbid every one of what qualitie or condition ſoever, to Tranſport out of our Kingdom any Gold or Silver, coined or uncoined, or any other Goldſmiths work, upon penaltie of forfeiture of the Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials and Merchandize, and other things therein they ſhall be found to be packed up in, beſides the penaltie of fiftie pounds, and bodily puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="ordinance">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:102645:30"/>
                  <head>In an ORDINANCE and PLACCART, For the Regulating of the Mint; Publiſhed in <hi>Bruſſels</hi> the laſt day of <hi>May,</hi> 1640.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. XI.</label> WE have alſo forbidden, and forbid by theſe preſents every one, of what quality or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoever, as well our Subjects as others, to tranſport any Gold or Silver from henceforth out of our Lands, directly or indirectly, or to cauſe the ſame to be tranſported, Minted or unminted, without having obtained from us before hand expreſs leave and conſent to do the ſame, upon penalty of forfeiture the Gold and Silver and Bullion, and to pay beſides the double worth, as alſo the Waggons that ſhall willingly have conveyed the ſame, the offenders to be baniſhed out of our land for five years, and the ſecond time for ever.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="ordinance">
                  <head>Ordinance and Placcart at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> the 18th. of March, 1643.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. LVII.</label> WE expresly forbid any perſon of what quality or condition ſoever to buy or ſell any Gold or Silver, either Bullion or currant, at a higher price then the Ordinance of our ſaid Mint permitteth, upon penalty of the forfeiture of all Gold and Silver the firſt time, the ſecond four times as much and ſevere correction.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="ordinance">
                  <head>Placcart and Ordinance for <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Antwerp.</hi> 4 Octob. 1585.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. XV.</label> WE forbid and interdict expresly that no one of what quality, or degree, or condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhall tranſport or carry any Gold or Silver of our Coins or Bullion, melted or in maſs, nor any Gold or Silver to coin money, upon forfeiture of the ſaid Gold and Silver, beſides two hundred Gold Roſe Nobles, for every Mark of Gold, and twenty Golden Roſe-Nobles for every Mark of Silver, and the ſecond time to be bodily puniſhed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. XIII.</label> ANd we do expresly forbid all and every one henceforth to buy or ſell any wares of Gold or Silver money at above the price of the Mint; for profit or gain, upon pain of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102645:30"/> ſeller to forfeit the pieces ſold, and the buyer as much as the ſeller; beſides, for the firſt time both buyer and ſeller to forfeit threeſcore pounds, and the third time to be arbitrarily puniſhed. </p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="ordinance">
                  <head>Placart and Ordinances concerning the general courſe and regulating of the Mint and Monies, as alſo concerning the Exchangers, Refiners, and Goldſmiths, and others in the united Provinces, 1646.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. XI.</label> ANd as for the Gold and Silver money whoſe value is rated by this Ordinance, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly forbid every one to preſent or pay, or receive the ſame at higher rates then are here ordered, upon forfeiture of ſuch money ſo exchanged, beſides arbitrary puniſhment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. XV.</label> VVE forbid every one to cull any Gold or Silver moneys, to ſort the weighty and good ones, from the light, for private and particular profit upon pain of forfeiture, or to buy any Silver for Work at higher rate then the Ordinance, upon pain of forfeiture double the value.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. XVII.</label> VVEe expreſsly forbid from henceforth to tranſport or cauſe to be tranſported out of our above-ſaid Province towards any ſtrange Mints, any Gold or Silver, Monies or Maſs or Ingots, fit to coin money, upon pain of Confiſcation of the above ſaid money and materials: And beſide the penalty of 100 golden Angelots upon every mark of Gold, and 20 Angelots for every mark of Silver, beſides for the ſecond time to ſuffer bodily puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>ARTIC. XXII.</label> VVEe forbid from henceforth every one to melt any Gold or other Moneys of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie of Englands ſtamp, valued by theſe Preſents upon penalty of life and goods, and the monies that ſhall be light, ſhall be brought to the Exchange according to the old Custome. If the Merchants pleaſe they may ſend to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and have all theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, and there they will ſee whether theſe Laws are not made according to the dates here aboveſaid, in <hi>France, Flanders, Holland:</hi> The whole buſineſs I humbly ſubmit at your Majeſties and your Priviy Councels feet, and humbly pray, I may ever live to ſee this Royall Prerogative of giving leave to tranſport Gold and Silver to be only in the Power of your Majestie, and your moſt Honourable Privie Council, that the Merchants greatneſs may be as a Handmaid to your Sacred Majeſty, and at your command always.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb facs="tcp:102645:31"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Do deſire the judicious Reader to pardon the miſtakes of the Preſs, and to mend them with his Pen, and the diſorder of ſorting my Notes, being ſtreightned in time, and fane to uſe two Preſſes for expedition, leaſt the Merchants ſhould have ſurprized his Majeſty, and gotten leave by Act of Parliament to Tranſport Gold and Silver at their pleaſure, to the damage of the Kings Majeſty, and his imperial Crown, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Grant me this juſt Requeſt, to mend the Errors with your Pen, and I ſhall be incouraged to preſent you with that which will be advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, which is, I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make an exact pare, and calculation of all the Gold and Silver Coins in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> their juſt weights and fineneſs, and what they will make, being full weight in his Majeſties Mint in the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and all the Figures, and Coins, Arms, and Mottoes ſeverally Engraven, which will be a work of charge, and pains, and will be a guide to all Merchants, to know all Forreign Coins of Gold and Silver in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> as well as our currant Coin of the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
